real madrid
[Music]
so
hello hello hello everybody are we live
i think we're live
good evening and good day to all of you
wherever you are i never imagined i
would be doing an ipl live stream on
this channel
but here we are so let's first see who
all is there i can see push rohit fox
bait siddhant trinai abhishek shlok
saket piyush hardik colvin
code officials anish
sujal
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you great to be with
you
watching an ipl match so
i am a huge fan of sports but i haven't
watched ipl in years in years it's been
like i don't know how many years it's
been i haven't watched the ipl i watched
the initial season of the ipl i thought
it was a very good idea to have a
professional league
for any kind of sport in india and i was
hoping that maybe it will
translate itself to hockey football
about the other things so there is some
of that happening but it's still not
taken off really in other sports
and ipl it's a good thing the thing is
uh about the ipl i have not seen for
many years because the thing is they
keep chopping and changing the teams
it's it's hard to follow a team
in a set of players and all that
but this year i thought let me get back
into watching
sport watching cricket
and i thought why not do a live stream
so as
so obviously i will not be streaming the
match over here because i don't want to
get sued by
the broadcasters and all that so i'm
going to be watching it i'm going to be
maybe doing some commentary and between
overs etcetera i'm gonna be taking
questions from you
and answering questions answering your
questions and having a conversation
so that is what i
so it's an experiment that i'm doing
let's see how it goes let's uh hang out
together watch sport watch cricket
and also we can do some q a and things
like that so i hope uh we can
do that so i think right now the match
is between delhi capitals and who else
is it
lsg what is lsg lucknow super giants i
don't even know these teams i mean they
keep on creating new teams how many
teams do you have in the ipl is it 10 is
it eight
not sure
and mr lee says please don't do
commentary just answer questions i'm
here to watch the match
i'm here to watch the match i'll also
answer questions how about that
uh so that's lsd so l
is it lsg lsd what is it
yeah somebody hersh is saying it is lsd
yeah right it's lsg lucknow supergiants
i think it's a new team that they have
come up with
and there is this team called delhi
capitals
so the match has not yet started i think
um they're showing
some kind of highlights or replays or
something so in the meanwhile
before the match starts if you have
questions
ask me questions and i'll be happy to
answer your questions
uh so i can see
there are no questions where did you
start where have you ended great to see
all right all right
you keep doing different things don't
you okay let's take some questions with
our non himanshu says with our
non-aligned stance we are pressing the
nerves of the us
so in is this in some way will impact
our economy and which block is good for
us because it will be difficult to be
neutral
in a bipolar world
we are not non-aligned india is not a
non-aligned nation anymore people still
have this hang up of the non-aligned
movement which is something that dates
back to the days of mr the great
the incredible
the magnificent mr nehru so
non-alignment is something that india
was following in those days and maybe
even later in the 21st century right now
india is not a non-aligned nation india
is aligned with itself india pursues its
own
interests so that's the stance of india
right now it is
not a non-aligned stance and of course
the u.s doesn't like it the u.s would
want india to be firmly in the u.s camp
and the u.s would want india to be
essentially
like the other western european nations
a de facto u.s colony that's what the
u.s would like to do now
i have spoken about this in the past
that the you in the west you have this
racist attitude towards india
well i would not characterize the u.s
behavior as racist behavior the u.s
behavior is the behavior of a bully
a bully
that's what they do to everybody they do
it with japan they do it with germany
they do it with france they do it with
the uk they do it with everybody right
now they're bullying russia
they have bullied ukraine and push them
into this confrontation with russia and
see who's suffering
so the us is trying to bully india as
well they want us to become their colony
they want us to toe their line democracy
is just for name namesake the so-called
rules-based international order it's you
know it's nice to talk about that but it
doesn't it exists only in in fiction
and in fantasy
so uh they are trying to bully us
and they want india to
cut off all
relations with moscow with mr putin with
russia and become a complete u.s colony
the quad
look at the members of the quad you have
japan which is a u.s colony you have
australia which is a u.s colony
who is the third
the third one is the u.s of course the
big bully and there's india so india is
the odd duck out in the quad the only
non-u.s colony
in the four
nation block so they want us also to
become a u.s colony they want us to
purchase all our arms and ammunition and
oil and gas and everything from the us
be completely dependent on the u.s
that's what they would like us to be
and obviously we will not do that
because it's not good for us a monopoly
is terrible
monopoly is a very asymmetric power
relation
so that's the kind of relation
the u.s seeks to establish
with all nations
and india is against that india wants to
remain autonomous
nowadays the term is strategic autonomy
or whatever it is it means that you are
aligned with your own national interest
and you will do what's best for yourself
so that's where we are today obviously
it is difficult to be neutral in a
bipolar world well the world is not yet
bipolar
the world is not yet bipolar the world
is right now multipolar the us wants a
bipolar world
and they are cajoling
the chinese into abandoning russia
and then we'll make the world bipolar
there are two big
impediments
to a bipolar world
there's not one big problem there are
two big problems there are that the
bipolarization proponents are
grappling with
the two big issues are russia and india
as long as russia and india pursue
independent foreign policies
and internal policies that are in tune
with their own self-interest as long as
that happens you will not have a bipolar
world
the us seeks a g2 kind of world with two
big poles the u.s led block and the
chinese lead block that's what they seek
that's what they would like to have they
would like to go go back to a cold
war-like scenario like we had in the
20th century that's what they seek but
as long as india exists and it's
reasonably independent and strong and
growing
and as long as russia also
is the way it is today you will not have
a bipolar world so the big
two big impediments are russia and india
there are no other big nations that can
play the role that india and russia can
play
so that's the problem and that's why
they're bullying us and they are
obviously
bullying the russians as well they have
imposed every single sanction you can
imagine on russia they i i heard today
that they even uh
sanctioned the two daughters of vladimir
putin and what did those two girls
ladies do i don't know anyway so there
are there are no rules
the so-called rules based international
order is a myth
right so himanshu you are right it is
going to be difficult to be neutral in a
bipolar world
so let's not make the world a bipolar
place
the world
the us would like the world to be
bipolar maybe even the chinese may like
it but right now it is not in china's
interests to have a starkly bipolar
world
a multipolar world is better for china
right now until they rise
to where they want to rise then they
would want a unipolar world not even a
bipolar world the chinese dream the
great dream of president xi jinping and
the great dream of the the great chinese
dream of the chinese communist party is
a monopolar unipolar world where china
is the center of the universe and
everybody comes and pays tribute to
china
so that is the great chinese dream
the chinese don't seek bipolarity the
chinese eventually want monopolarity
unipolarity
so that's the
conflict we are seeing right now the u.s
wants bipolarization the chinese seek a
monopolar world
india as it as it stands in russia also
as it stands would want to have a
multi-polar world
so there are these the us
has has a certain
world that they want to create
they envisage a certain kind of world
the chinese in visage a different kind
of world
india
in visage is hopefully a certain kind of
world and so on so forth so there are
these different world views they are
currently
in conflict with each other
so that's where we are it's it's
obviously going to be difficult for
india it's going to be it's right right
now it's a tight rope walk that we are
doing we are walking
we are doing a very very fine balancing
act so uh
what india needs is to grow its economy
grow the economy if your economy grows
your military strength also grows your
influence grows and as long as you don't
bully other nations and exploit other
nations you will be able to attract
like-minded nations with yourself right
now india and france have a very good
relationship you could call it a
strategic kind of relationship and so on
and the french have always resisted
american bullying they are a member of
nato
but they don't do the line of the us and
the u.s has been punishing them on and
off for that for instance the french had
this submarine deal with the australians
and the australians who are u.s colony
had to break off the deal and now they
have decided to purchase extremely
expensive american submarines
to please the masters so the french
certainly have been left with nothing
and they are very unhappy with that
obviously they would be right why won't
you be why would you be happy with that
sort of thing
so
as you can see the us is a big bully i
mean you you are that size you will be a
bully
i mean you can choose to be a bully
so that's the kind of world we are
living in we don't india
for for from india's perspective we
don't want a bipolar world we want a
multi-polar world we need to resist
any attempt to make the world a bipolar
place because if there are only two
polls that india is not significant
insignificant and so is russia and so so
is anybody else it means you have two
monopolies on power and everything else
it means if the world becomes bipolar it
means that india would either be
completely destroyed fragmented or
india's economy will be completely uh
subsidiary to another nation's economy
most likely the u.s so not good
not good
so for india we don't want a bipolar
world that's what i can say
okay today i've kept the
uh what is it called super chat on
because why not it's been a year
so there is the super chat question by
pratik why is zelensky not understanding
the destruction of his country and other
parties stopping him to stop the war and
agree to russian demands so somebody
asked me uh i don't know last week or
something
what is the national interest and how
does every nation decide what its
national interest is is there some
organization institute or something that
decides what the national interest is
and tells the leader what to do or not
and the answer is
most nations unfortunately don't follow
their national interest
if you have a corrupt leader
let's look at sri lanka
see what happened in sri lanka the sri
lanka took this ridiculous loans from
the chinese
was it in line with sri lanka's national
interest to take loans with such
ridiculous
interest rates and repayment terms and
all that it essentially makes sri lanka
a chinese colony and yet the sri lankans
did that under the rajapaksas
why is that
because china has what's known as
checkbook diplomacy they will tell the
leader the corrupt leader of a country
what do you need
what's your price you tell me your price
i'll pay you and then you do this thing
you sign on the dotted line you take up
this loan and that's it then you can go
and enjoy your life
and we'll take deal with your country
so
in the case of zelensky
he's not a democratically
see what happened in 2014 was a coup
in in ukraine
there was a democratically elected
government it was ousted
undemocratically and unconstitutionally
per the ukrainian constitution
and
a new leadership was put in place which
was
a u.s puppet regime
and zelensky is a continuation of that
right
so now if he is in the u.s pocket
obviously he will do what the u.s wants
the u.s wants to use ukraine as the
cannon fodder to start a war with russia
a big conflict with russia and they hope
to destroy the russian economy
destroy russia and hopefully if if
things go really bad then maybe even
putin will be ousted from power and then
then they will have this they will be
able to achieve they'll be one step
closer to the dream
of a bipolar world
so zelensky is a puppet
zelensky doesn't care about his national
interest
that's my
assessment of zelinski you may disagree
some people may disagree fine
let's agree to disagree from my
perspective zelensky
who does zelinski solve
the the crucial question when it comes
to leaders
is very simple who does he or she serve
and how do you decide
how do
you determine who a leader serves not by
their words zelensky is good at talking
he's a he's an entertainer he's an actor
comedian right so he'll be good at
talking he'll be good at giving great
speeches
inspiring inspirational speeches but
look at the actions and look at where
those actions have taken his country oh
the match is starting
jason holder is bowling anyway
so yeah so that's the thing
zelinski is yeah he is he's leading his
country towards destruction his country
no longer exists the way it
existed you know in february in the
first week of february
uh you're gonna have big bites taken out
of ukraine novorossiya will be created
by the russians there will be a rump
state to the west even the belarusians
will maybe take some pieces out of
ukraine and whatever and even if
zelensky stays in power
he's gonna be
a leader only in name
right
the russians have very clear demands
you agree that you will not ever be part
of
nato
you be neutral
and then
that's what they seek
but obviously zelensky has certain
masters
who he has to please and he essentially
is a sock puppet
what is a sock puppet is a puppet that
you wear on your hand and then you
then you make the mouth speak but
actually it's your voice that comes out
so he's a sock puppet of the us of the
west of nato
now people say that i am very very
anti-west and all that i mean
look at the actions of the west in the
past 500 years
so that's just what it is right so that
is what's happening that's why zelensky
is not understanding he understands very
well what's happening he can see in
front of his eyes what's happening to
his country it's possible that he's no
longer in his country
it's possible that he's somewhere else
and pretending to be in his country with
a nice green screen behind him see when
you have a green screen you can put any
kind of background behind you in my case
i don't have a green screen i have real
stuff here but if i put a green screen
behind me i could pretend like i'm in
new york or manhattan or or tokyo or
wherever i want on a beach
so
so that's what it is right
that is what zelensky is is up to
unfortunately he is not really
representing the people of ukraine he
doesn't have their best interests in at
heart
and there is something in it for him
also right because he is now he has now
been elevated to the level of a che
guevara or something by the west
and so on so forth
so that is where mr zelensky is and that
is the thing about him now let me see
what is the situation with the match
it looks like it is live now
lsg won the toss and chose to bowl
and three four no loss after three three
balls good
and mr holder is bowling
to whom to mr warner mr warner the
australian
yeah mr warner very very nice guy
you know his history right he was
involved in that what is it called the
sandpaper gate
australians
i mean i have been watching cricket for
law i'm a huge fan of sport okay
i'm a huge fan of sport i used to love
playing sport whenever i was allowed to
as a kid
i'm a very i'm a very
in in public life i'm a very calm quiet
person you know you may not see me that
way because
i do talk but i'm usually a quiet person
right
so as a kid i was a very quiet kid
mostly but when i was on the sports
field my my true personality would come
out i am a very competitive person i
enjoy sport any kind of sport i've
always been a bookworm i read a lot but
the only thing that prevented me from
becoming a complete nerd like like
people would say is that i'm i love
sport i'm good at sport and i enjoy
sport
so uh i
have been in india that's only cricket
mostly right so i was watching
i watched test cricket for a long time
and i would notice something about
australians
whenever they would come to india on
these flat pitches their bowlers the
australian bowlers would get the ball
the ball to swing
on indian pitches
and indian bowlers would not get the
same kind of swing
glenn mcgrath the australian fast bowler
medium pacer he would get the ball to
swing the like nobody else could on
indian pitches i always wondered how is
it that he gets to do this
clearly there was some sandpaper
involved
right
anyway let's see some more questions um
aussies are very racist do you feel that
i do feel so i do feel that
it's not just a question of the
australians it's the english-speaking
people
who are
very racist they are
the english the anglo culture is
different from european culture even
europeans in mainland europe have a
history of racism no doubt about that
but the english-speaking world is at a
higher level level
of racism
in the case of the us
i think i mean i've lived there on three
different occasions
in the us
you don't face the kind of racism you
face in europe actually but when it
comes to the uk and all their attitude
is that when the australians
well um
you know what ian botham said about the
australians
uh what did he say about australia he
said it would be great to go and play in
sydney in front of a hundred thousand
convicts that's what he said that's not
my words
that is the words of ian botham so the
australians the if you know the history
it's very interesting the
the original australian population was a
population of convicts were transported
from
from england from the uk
permanently to this island
so there were there were two choices you
are either executed
you know killed or you are transported
forever so that's how it was so the
original population of the australians
the white australians
was convicts were transported there for
life so australia was essentially an
open prison a continent-sized prison and
it was stolen land obviously
the true natives of australia the true
australians are
what is now called the australian
aborigines aborigines uh
aboriginal people
it is their land that the whites have
stolen the english-speaking people have
stolen so there's a
incredible amount of racism in australia
they have a history of being racist and
you will see that coming out on the
cricket field nowadays
nowadays it's all nice nice no no no
racism is bad but historically they've
been very racist
okay sheila aditya says you went oh my
god
mr shiladitya says you went from being
an astrophysicist to a far right
conspiracy theorist
spreading propaganda for the ruling
party and our supreme leader wow
unemployment
obviously
whatever all right so thank you for your
for your inputs i appreciate it and it's
very nice of you to
even
okay whatever
i i wish i wish i was paid
for whatever i say but no nothing
sadly
all right let's go somewhere else
um
are you
aware about cue t one nation one exam
what's your take on this is this the
first step towards standardization
in the education system of india
i am not quite sure what c-u-e-t is one
nation one exam sounds like a very good
idea
one nation one exam i mean that's
something we should have
so that everyone knows where they stand
from a from a
integrated perspective for instance if
you have somebody who
somebody at the 10 standard level in
let's say assam somebody in gujarat
somebody in tamil nadu and they all have
different boards and they all have
different ways of grading
the marks for instance it's it's quite
common i believe in maharashtra to have
99 100
uh marks that people get in their exams
whereas in some other states even 70
would be an extraordinary achievement so
how do you judge who stands where in
comparison to each other there has to be
standardization
at a national scale
so if
such a scheme is
being implemented or possibly
going to be implemented in the future
it's a very good thing i welcome it but
i still haven't heard about that
and the thing is education well
it's one thing to pass exams but do you
actually learn something that's the
other thing you do consider so the
education system needs to be overhauled
i mean at a very deep level
and it needs a fundamental overhaul it's
not just about having it's it's a good
step to have a one nation one exam kind
of system
but the exam also should actually
test how much you know how much you have
actually learned something as as opposed
to how much you can memorize
because you memorize for the exam next
week once you give the exam you can
forget it because you don't need that
anymore the purpose is served but that
doesn't really
help you progress in life and give you
any real skills and confidence to deal
with the world
so that's what i can say but i will look
it up what the cut thing is
i will look it up for sure
all right let's take some questions so i
am not looking at the ipl at all
i should
okay let's take harsha's question
what's the future of u.s ties if it as
per the latest news to decide what's
better for us can we afford to act like
the saudis or submit to the new world
order it all depends on how strong we
are if we are strong enough powerful
enough
if
in that case we can do what is in our
national interest if we are weak like
the germans like the japanese then we
will have to submit
to the greater power the us so india is
in a good position reasonably compared
to nations like japan nations like
australia nations like the uk nations
like new zealand or germany
or ukraine india is in a much better
position we are a much
we have a very good geographical
location in the indian ocean region we
have a good growing economy we have
excellent people we have a very
vibrant young population who have a lot
of potential so we have these things the
thing is
our leaders need to find a way to have
another
decade or two decades
of peace and stability
and
that if we do that then our economy will
grow to
and it will cross the 10 trillion dollar
mark and that's what we need you know
so the future of ties
it depends see the us like i said is a
bully it's a big bully it bullies
everybody not just india
i mean
look at the way it deals with uh
germany
look at the way it deals with japan
australia is is is essentially a u.s
corporation
that's what australia is australia is a
us corporation new zealand is like
it's it's in the pocket of australia so
it's not even dealt with by the u.s it's
dealt with australia so compared to all
that
india is in a much better position now
how do you deal with a bully how do you
deal with the blackmailer
if you give in to blackmail the
blackmail will continue in installments
if you
give in to a bully you're gonna get
bullied every day
it's never gonna stop if you're given
once it's gonna continue
to deal with a bully you're gonna stand
up to the bully and say it's not gonna
work sorry i can deal with you
so that's what india needs to do india
needs to find the right way of doing it
india needs to
walk the tight rope which is
happening right now india has a very
good foreign minister and a very good
foreign policy the best foreign policy i
have seen during my lifetime and before
my lifetime we did not even have a
foreign policy so uh
so yeah things are fine things are
better i would say
um
okay what else do we have let's see some
more questions many ways okay let's see
ayan my good friend ayan there are many
waves of migration and there has been a
recent archaeological discovery in tamil
nadu
which proves that dravidian settled
before north indians
i am not aware of any archaeological
discovery that
tells you it is a dravidian settlement
or
okay
we have to ask ourselves a very
fundamental question
this aryan dravidian divide that we
speak about
everybody has bought into this and i
don't blame everybody for buying into it
that's what we are taught from the
moment we are born the moment we go to
school
is there any mention
of the word aryan and dravidian in any
indian literature any indian history
in ethnic terms
in sanskrit the word arya exists
even south indian southern indian people
are called aryas
it depends on your behavior
on your character and your personality
if you if your behavior is noble you are
real so it's an adjective it's not an
ethnic term
our persian cousins who left india many
thousand years ago they started using
that as an ethnic term
so that is something that they did we
never did that
no so so the uh so the term aryan is a
foreign term it's crea it's been created
by the
or the english-speaking people to divide
the country once again with with the
term dravidian where do you find in
let's say the sangam literature in the
the pm or whatever do you find the term
dravidian somewhere
no you don't find it yeah somebody will
will pull out something somewhere
some term somewhere once it was used
apparently
[Music]
or something like that and they have
turned that into dravidian so these are
inventions
now i am not aware of
if you
have a link or something i'll be happy
to take a look at it but i am not aware
of any archaeological discovery that
proves anything
that dravidians came first or aryans
came first or north indians came first
come on man we know for a fact that the
indian population that
lives in india today
uh has genetic lineages both patrilineal
and matrilineal lineages that date back
60 70 000 years
whether you're living in north india or
south india or east or west wherever
right
and even the people from
from eastern asia
even their deep genetic lineages deep
genetic genetic ancestry
goes back to ancient india 60 70 000
years ago
so that's where we are and that's what i
can say about this um
right
do you miss gail and amy de villiers
uh yeah gail was good he was very
entertaining universe boss
abd i don't know what happened i think
he
he got old or something
he retired and then he tried to come
back did not work the thing about sports
is that after a certain age
especially if you're a better batsman
you don't do well it's not because your
physical ability is diminished because
your eyesight
slowly
imperceptibly
becomes weaker
the reason why
these batsmen in the after they reach
the age of 33 34 why does their ability
diminish it's because the eyesight it
becomes slightly weaker over time
you know so they can't see the ball
they can't track the ball the way they
used to when they were 25 or even 30. so
that's what happened so yeah it was fun
while it lasted gail wasn't was
entertaining so was abd villairs
but i'm sure there are new
interesting cricketers around
and i can see mr pretty shaw is batting
right now and he's hammering the ball
there's a guy called avesh
who's bowling
and once again the ball goes to the
boundary
so delhi capitals
31 for knowledge and 35 and 3.3 hours
there used to be a team called deccan
chargers right what happened to decon
charges i wonder
deck in charges is gone apparently
okay let's see what shubham says i
recently got into reading non-fiction
books because of your recommendation of
books
in history astrophysics i request you to
kindly provide to provide some more book
recommendations
sure
i think it's time for me to do one more
book recommendation video so maybe that
should be coming up
soon
i could recommend ten thousand books of
course but maybe i'll do a curated list
of books
okay let's see uh aveish is still
bowling and bang the ball goes to the
boundary again my god
the thing i don't quite like about the
ipl is there is no balance between baton
ball
every ball even in the first two three
hours goes to the boundary
i have never seen the ball swing in the
ipl why is that
do they make these special kinds of
balls that don't swing
i don't get it
there should be some sort of balance
between baron ball
i like the ball where it swings
it's fun to watch and it makes life a
little difficult for the batsman
but i suppose it's not good for the
spectators the spectators want to see
fours and sixes
and that's why
that's why maybe they are using all
these flat pitches i'm sure even the
australians are doing that in their big
bash legal whatever they call whatever
they call it
again the ball bang
this time not to the boundary
okay anish says why isn't cricket as
popular as football and it isn't played
by as many nations as football
even though apparently both the sports
were invented in the uk
i think cricket needs a lot of
specialized equipment
you need a bat
you need two bats
at least one bat you need a certain kind
of ball
then you need a pitch with a certain
kind of dimensions you need six stumps
you need bales
you need two umpires
you need a big ground
as far as football goes all you need is
a ball that ball you know
and you can use any kind of ball you can
even use a basketball if you have
nothing else
or a volleyball
ball or something so i think it's much
easier to start playing football than to
play qriket and cricket obviously has
all these rules
in football the objective is very clear
go and put the ball in the net that's it
there are two nets you need to score
goals
in cricket there are so many rules so
many ways of getting out so many ways of
all kinds of other things right so
cricket is way more complex than
football so maybe there is a reason why
it hasn't really caught on now
now was cricket really invented in the
uk
was it now was it
so
what is what what some people say is
that the english
mistakenly by mistake
they
invented an indian sport or they
discovered an indian sport so i think if
you look at the history of cricket
it's uh it goes back like 300 400 years
there used to be a game they used to
play which was
which is the precursor
to what we call cricket today
and
it uh
it has its origins in england apparently
but if you look at ancient indian
stories i mean if you look at the
if you i'm sure most of you should
should have some passing familiarity
with the life story
of lord krishna the early stories of his
childhood etc he used to play on the
banks of the river yamuna and what did
he play
along the banks of the yamuna there is
this great story right that he's playing
a
game of bat and ball
and the ball goes and falls in the river
and there is this great
serpent
kali nag who lives in the in the in the
river
and he refuses to give the ball back and
then krishna has to go and defeat him so
what sport was krishna playing
what game was lord krishna playing as a
kid he was playing a game of bat and
ball
wasn't it
there you go
they just says at the time of the second
battle of tarain
why didn't other hindu kings help
prithviraj it's very simple there was a
lack of unity political unity in india
at that time india was not unified under
a single
central
uh
political leadership like it was from
time to time in the past
we had political unity during the
mauryan era
starting from
emperor chandragupta maurya
we had political unity even to some
extent during the
shunga era
which was the successor state of the
morius
we had political unity during the time
of the questions especially during the
time of the great emperor kanishka
we had the same during the gupta age
and
during the time of lalitha
peda and then you had a different kind
of political unity during the time of
for the cholas i mean the zenith the
golden age of the cholas which extended
into southeast asia
so during the
time of the
turkic invasions
you did not have political unity in
northern india
you had these small kingdoms with these
petty rivalries among each other
most of these were these old
aristocratic dynasties which are now
known as rajputs in those days they were
not known as rajput the rajputs they
were simply kings
so um
so they had these little rivalries with
each other petit petty rivalries for
land and prestige and all that
and unfortunately when some misfortune
befell one of them the others would feel
that it's good for me
it will advance my political interests
so that's what happened
they did not realize what these turkic
invaders were up to
that they actually sought to uproot and
destroy indian civilization completely
and even if they had known this they may
have thought it's not a big deal we can
deal with them later or whatever it is
so that's the problem
when you
have a civilization that is this big you
need
political unity you need central
you need a central leadership
centralized leadership
so that's what subhash chandra bose was
was to create
he actually
could not succeed because of a variety
of factors
so that's what i can say there's a break
going on in cricket
cricket
right
okay
let's see what the questions who is your
favorite
nadal djokovic or federer
i think there is something that you can
admire in all three of them
the work ethic it's not enough to be
talented
talent is overrated there are lots of
people who are talented but they achieve
nothing because they don't have the
willingness the capability the capacity
to work really hard
to be disciplined to be dedicated
so we know what kind of work ethic
people like djokovic and nadal and
federer have they would never have been
able to win 20 plus grand slam titles
individually each
without an insane amount of
you know insane amount of discipline a
great work work ethic
so i admire that there is something we
should all try to emulate from people
who succeed at a very high level
so among all these three guys who who is
my favorite maybe joko which maybe maybe
joker
i used to admire federer a lot he's very
pleasing to watch he's got the most
aesthetic and effortless
style of tennis the most uh difficult
game
the the one that seems to put in the
greatest amount of effort is nadal he
seems to put like 200 percent into every
stroke right whereas with federer it
looks effortless
and joko which also
he looks kind of effortless so yeah i
think djokovic is the guy i like
the best
all right um
my thoughts on iits
the iits unfortunately are no longer as
good as they used to be i think the
downfall of the iits began in the
in the early 2000s
when they started
implementing reservations in the iits
so the iits became a joke after that i
think it was the congress party the
congress government the upa government
and i think the education minister i i
believe if i am not mistaken it was mr
sibal
kapil sibal
so he's the guy who ruined the iits
so today the iits are
there was a time when the iits used to
be in the top 10
institutions when it comes to science
and technology in the world
that's how good the iits were
today the iits are not even in the top
hundred so that's what they've done to
the iits
and once you impose
reservations somewhere you can't remove
them because otherwise you're gonna
you're gonna
suffer politically so every political
party has to do it
so today the iits are a joke
i'm not saying reservations are good or
bad of course they are bad everybody
should get the same treatment
there should be complete meritocracy in
the country reservations
not a bad idea completely
but if you want to implement
reservations you have to implement them
on the basis of financial situation
financial status not your births
you belong to so so class or cast or
whatever then you will get an automatic
reservation that's nonsense
there are people from all classes all
all so-called castes
who are extremely prosperous but they're
they're given reservations it's stupid
so
that's what i feel about it the iits are
terrible
there's a lot of money that the iits
have but the money is wasted and i've
said this many times that
if you go to an iit
then you will find that the uh
that the washrooms
uh they have invested millions of
dollars in the washrooms very nice
luxurious and all that if you look at
the conference rooms and meeting rooms
very well equipped air conditioned and
all very expensive but if you go to the
lab and see the equipment it's 20 30
years old so they are wasting the money
where it's not supposed to be spent
so it's because the iits are run by
these idiotic moronic bureaucrats
including the heads of departments and
all that who are idiots
see in india in the indian education
system if you want to rise if you want
to get promotions in the academic system
you have to be good at playing politics
and not good necessarily at science or
whatever you're teaching
but you have to be good involved in
playing politics so the people who rise
to the top
mostly
90 percent of the people who rise to the
top are politicians and administrators
and bureaucrats that sort of mindset and
not scientists
so it's it's mediocrity rewarding
mediocrity and that's the vicious cycle
that you see in the iits
sadly
okay let's find the next comment
something uh
india should start negotiating with sri
lankan territories in exchange for aid
etc before china or imf intervenes well
if you do that then they're going to
call india an expansionist nation
because india should never do such
things other countries can do it
but if india does it very bad
so that's the attitude you have
i think
there's a better way of doing it
you could have a eu kind of system
in which you have sovereign nations but
there is an integrated economy in all
that
so there are various ways of achieving
a more integrated indian subcontinent
and maybe beyond that also but that will
take time
chandra khan says any thoughts on
decentralized streaming services ott is
over the tops as they call it these days
i'm planning to create one in the next
few years that's very good i really like
this idea
and i wish you the best
uh decentralized streaming services are
good i mean there's a lot there's a
whole bouquet of them that you can
choose from today so they give people
options options are always good
there are some really big ones like
netflix and
hot star on which i'm watching the the
cricket right now
so there are big ones there are smaller
ones also
there are some that are geared towards
towards video like
uh
live telecasts and uh
tv series and that sort of thing there
are some that are geared towards music
for instance and so on so forth so it's
good
the more options you have the better
your life is and the more power you have
to decide what you want to do with your
life
in the past
in the 20th century
the entire world especially the western
world you would have these dozens of tv
channels but in india
you had only one tv channel and they
used to call it duk darshan
it was terrible
it was based in new delhi
and it would have these sessions they
used to call it sabha subaiki
so there will be a three hour session in
the in the morning
then a six hour session or something in
the evening and then there will be this
atrocious news
which would be all about which minister
said what today that sort of thing the
people of india had no choice they were
forced to watch only one tv channel and
the government would not allow any other
thing to come up
so that created a very unhealthy
monopoly
on everything
so that is not good
so these decentralized streaming
services that give people lots of
options
you can pick and choose what you like so
it's a good thing
of course there are problems as well
like for instance there is a lot of
hindu phobic content on certain
such services
so that is for the government the people
to address but overall conceptually it's
a very good thing so i'm really glad
that you're planning to create one in
the next few years and i wish you all
the best may you succeed sir
all right
so what's happening on the ipl front
they can know what are the daily
capitals
54 for no loss in six point three hours
brittany
is a
british english surname isn't it
so why is this indian guy who has no
british blood whatsoever why is he
called shaw
with three
sure looks like he got to 50 now of 30
balls he's raising his back yeah baby
good job
i wonder why indians
are so
what's what's the history of this
surname sure why does an indian guy have
a foreign surname
uh sorry what is this
joseph says why do indians love sports
where it's one versus many like coco
cricket and kabaddi anything with our
mentality
um
that's an interesting question
so uh when it comes to sports like
cricket
it's it started from england so
yeah it's obviously taken root in india
anything to do with our mentality you
know if you have a one against many
mentality it's not necessarily a bad
thing
oh somebody got out
i think
no no it's not out anyway
uh when it comes to khabardi khabab is a
very interesting sport it's an indian
sport or our
parsi brothers and sisters also played
kabaddi
and coverd is actually two teams but
yeah you have to go and
do the thing raiding or whatever as an
individual against the entire group
it's a very interesting sport it's a
contact sport
contrary to many other sports it's a
contact sport you need strength you need
bulk
physical
mass and all that in some cases and so
on so it's a good sport
so
and i believe that even football is
quite popular in india it's just that it
has never taken off because
the right kind of money
has not gone into it there is this
indian
isl or something there is an ipl like
league for football also i think but
it's not quite taken off i think there's
less money in it
if you put in more money it'll take off
and
another spot i am quite fond of is
hockey hockey is
brilliant i love hockey hockey is very
exciting it's incredibly fast paced
i can't watch hockey sitting down i've
got to stand and watch it you know
especially when when india is playing
so that again is not a one against many
sport it's it's a
it's a balanced sport like football so i
don't think there is any such thing it's
just that for some reason
uh
the anglophilic aristocracy or elite
so-called elite of india loved cricket
very much because
they were in love with everything all
things british
and that's why that sport got a lot of
impetus
after
the transfer of power in 1947
coco
i'm not very sure about coco i think
there are two teams in cocoa
i've always
seen it as a girls sport or sport that
girls play maybe i'm wrong but i don't
know much about coco
it's obviously an indian indigenous game
so
i don't think there is any specific
mentality that this reflects it's about
the mentality of the people
who who promoted certain sports
so that's that's what i could say about
that
do you like test cricket test cricket
it's good i like it it's brilliant it
takes a lot of time so you don't get to
you don't have the time to watch it much
similar to chess
i mean there was a time when i used to
love chess a lot when i was when i was a
kid
but
afterwards i stopped playing because it
takes so much time out of your day
you play a game of chess especially when
you get engrossed in it you may easily
spend two three hours doing that yeah
right
so um
yeah i do like this cricket i like chess
also but i don't have the time anymore
to watch watch test cricket i don't i
don't mind watching the highlights or
watching a half an hour session or
something
but test cricket obviously is the real
real test of your ability as a cricketer
so yes i do like
test cricket
oh finally somebody asks me about
science these days i talk very less
about science because i don't get
questions about science so the question
by shaury is what is dark matter
dark matter is
it consists i mean if you look at the
mass energy composition of the universe
our brahmand
we live in the universe
we sit on this little planet earth the
earth goes around the sun and there are
other planets as well that is the solar
system
our solar system is just one tiny little
speck of dust in the galaxy
which we call the milky way
the milky way is a little speck of dust
in the local super cluster of galaxies
that we inhabit
and that itself is just a small little
filament in the big
large scale structure of the universe
the observable universe is about 90 95
trillion light
billion light years
across
in the
universe that we can't observe may be
way way larger than that so we don't
know how big the universe actually is
so if you look at the observable
universe and you calculate
the mass energy the matter energy
composition then you find that
everything that we see
all the stars all the galaxies all the
planets all the dust everything
is just about four percent
of the universe
about 70 percent is what we call
dark energy
and the remaining
portion of the universe is dark matter
so dark matter is some kind of substance
that we know exists because it causes
effects like gravitational lensing
it causes galaxies to rotate at a
certain speed which they would not if
there was no dark matter and so on so
forth so that is what dark matter is it
is an unknown mysterious substance that
interacts only gravitationally it
doesn't interact via the strong force or
the weak force or the electromagnetic
interaction only gravitation most likely
so that's what dark matter is what is it
i
we still don't know there are theories
there are
multiple theories as to what dark matter
could be
thus far we have not been able to
find the answer and that's why it's so
interesting
there are big mysteries out there that
we still that we still haven't uh
resolved
is messy and alien it's possible that he
may be an alien i mean unless we go and
examine we will not know right so we
only can see him from far away
or on the screen
so yeah it is possible it's possible
that even i may be an alien
as far as you're concerned anything is
possible
so yeah
coco is a very interesting game
unfortunately you don't get to watch
coco
we don't even
have any exposure to it
in the
in the media
so i'm sure it's very interesting there
are lots of indigenous games in india
that most of us don't know about which
is which is sad you know
all right
vasso agarwal your views on the
bucha buca i don't know what it's called
massacre in ukraine
so listen um
there are all kinds of claims that have
been made
the ukrainians and nato and all they are
saying that the russians have done it
the russians are giving evidence that
shows that this is all staged
and
according to the russians this is what's
known as a false flag operation
what's a false flag operation it's when
you do something
which
harms your own interest and then you use
that as
to blame somebody else
and then you take that as the pretext to
conduct a larger military operation for
instance
so some people some
let's call them conspiracy theorists
just to be safe
so some conspiracy theorists
and historians would say that pearl
harbor
was a false flag operation
some people would say that the gulf of
tonkin incident
which precipitated the vietnam war was a
false flag incident so you do something
you you knock out one of your ships let
some of your own people die and then you
say that the other side has done it and
then you start to use that to start a
war
so that's called a false flag operation
the russians are saying the ukrainians
have carried out a false flag operation
to blame the russians and maybe then
they can dig for the nato guys can take
further action against russia use that
as a pretext that's what the russians
are claiming the ukrainians are claiming
if the russians have done it
the americans are claiming the russians
have done it so we don't know we don't
know
right
who do we trust
you don't trust anybody you have to look
at the evidence
and the evidence is inconclusive sitting
here
so that's my views but i am not inclined
to blindly trust anybody
hmm that's what i would say
all right let's
see
are you a bowler a batsman or an
all-rounder i used to be a bowler
so i spent a few years
as a kid in europe
so that's when you develop all the
skills and all that so when i returned
to india
i found that there's only one sport that
people play in india which is cricket
and everybody wants to back
and by that age everybody had already
learned how to the technique of batting
and all that
so then i was left with no option but to
learn how to bowl and i found that i
enjoyed it so i was a bowler
i started off as a leg spinner
then as i grew taller i saw i became a
fast bowler i enjoyed swinging the ball
and all that
so i was never a good batsman half the
time i would bat left handed half time
right handed
so
that's how it was i used to be a bowler
i was a leg spinner first and then a
fast bowler base bowler
aditya says do you have information
about indian workouts or wrestling
culture
i do wrestling myself wanted to know
more about its history in india so in
india we have a very old
history of wrestling right if they
these days they call it kushti or
something
on the
so
there are these akhadas etc
or or these training camps training
schools or whatever for wrestlers and
there are these traditions that go back
hundreds of years centuries maybe
thousands of years so indians
i think from the days of lord hanuman
were good at wrestling
it's one of the most basic sports that
you can do one guy against another guy
and a test of strength according to a
certain rules you follow certain rules
you don't do certain things and that's
what you do so uh
india has a very ancient wrestling
culture that probably goes back many
thousands of years
um
so very that hasn't been documented well
our historians obviously have no
interest in documenting our real history
they only want to glorify the mughals
and the british and so on and so forth
so there's so much that can be
so much interesting research that can be
done in in our indian history
the history of indian music for instance
the history of indian sport the various
sports that we have in india we had
various martial arts in india that have
disappeared today
the martial art that uh
that
bodhidharma took to china
it's it no longer exists in india
some people say it's colored by youtube
what's the evidence
there's no evidence it's colored too
is very very different from kung fu
and kung fu is what came out of the
martial art that bodhidharma taught in
china
so we have a very ancient history of
martial arts of sports wrestling is a
martial art isn't it
so we had a variety of martial arts
they have all more or less gone extinct
we have kalari pyotu in southern india
in present-day kerala
which may have an old history i i don't
know personally how old the history is
we used to have various uh
martial arts in northern india there is
one that still kind of persists is
called shastra vidya
then there was the rajput art of sword
fighting
which
still exists to some extent in the form
of the dandiya dance
and so on so um
so i don't have any specific information
unfortunately about the history of
indian wrestling i wish our professional
historians would delve into this because
there's it's a fascinating fascinating
topic
okay
why indians
are not accepting a single language
english language is killing local talent
and they feel humiliated always
i agree the english language is
what keeps mentally colonized including
people like me
so
the thing is india is a land
of thousands of languages and dialects
everybody should be given
education in
not more than one or two languages the
mother tongue has to be the primary
medium of instruction
and maybe a national language or a
civilization language
for which there's only one
candidate only one
sanskrit
not hindi not english
hindi is a local language in a certain
part of northern india it has been
forcibly imposed on the rest of india
and via hindi
they have brought in urdu which is
essentially
a prakrit language with foreign
vocabulary
and
they have kind of tried to portray urdu
urdu as superior
right so they have used hindi as the
back door to introduce introduce urdu
and foreign words into the indian
consciousness and vocabulary
so the only language that i view
as india's civilizational language
which
which there's only one which is
obviously sanskrit and
no other language can replace sanskrit
but they have essentially more or less
succeeded in killing of
sanskrit
so you are right that the english
language is destroying killing local
talent
and everybody feels humiliated those who
can't speak english well why should you
be able to speak english well
i mean it's not your language
and
these days it's like if you don't speak
english well it means you're not
intelligent enough that's the kind of
attitude that teachers have which is
nonsense
can you please go to china unscripted
podcast and have a session with mr chris
chapel hmm
never heard of it unfortunately
but if mr chris chapel invites me i will
look into it
babe sharma says why do you love nehru
so much you keep on saying such great
words
about him
well why would you not love somebody as
great as mr nero
there has never been a prime minister of
india as great as the great great shri
shri shri
bahala
a man of such incredible and immense
achievements
he wrote a scholarly book
he was a global statesman
he started an entire movement
non-aligned movement
he even achieved the kind of rate of
growth that was so hard to achieve in
any developing country the nehru rate of
growth
and
so many other achievements i mean where
do we begin
so obviously one must express express
one's admiration
for a man of his structure
right so what's happening in the ipl
deck
i keep calling it deck and charges
does the deccan chargers team still
exist i'm not sure
all right ayush says
can our missile defense systems radar
identify our own helicopters and jets to
prevent our own damage
there was an incident of our own
helicopter crash mi 75 in friendly fire
2019 indo pack
i believe advanced
systems have a iff
identification mechanism if friend or
foe
so
it should be able to if you have the
technology
it should be able to identify whether it
is your asset
or somebody else's asset
so what what do we what we mean by your
own asset means your own helicopter or
your own plane
so i believe we have the technology and
the ability to do that friendly fire is
something that you can never completely
prevent
it happens everywhere
and that's one of the one of the
hazards
of warfare
sometimes you're going to end up
end up
firing on your own people and assets
that happens
especially when there is a evolving
situation in the so-called fog of war
so i think we do have that technology
and the one hopes that it doesn't happen
again
okay what is what else do we have the
brand value of the ipl is around 9
billion us dollars
if expanded further can the ipl in the
future contribute in the indian economy
and act as soft power
for india just like the epl i think
sports has a great amount of potential
to contribute
to a nation's economy and soft power
the epl is a very good example you
mentioned the english premier league
lots of people watch these
this league from all across the world
people are big fans of whatever team
liverpool or manchester united or
whatever it is
there are indians who buy all the
merchandise the t-shirts and all that
and wear it very proudly so that
increases this foreign country's soft
power in india because india admires
that league and those players and so on
so if
the ipl can be expanded made larger
it would certainly
help the indian economy
and promote indian soft power
right now the ips's ipl is like a circus
it's a one month or so tournament a
proper league is about eight to nine
months of a year
right so right now the ipl is not at
that stage the ipl has only one um
what is it
it has only one rung right only some 10
teams or so there are no you need to
have several divisions for a proper
league so division a division b that
sort of thing
so the ipl is still i would say in its
infancy it it certainly has potential
so if it is done properly it can
certainly
contribute to the economy it can create
an entire ecosystem of jobs trainers
grounds people
um
sports people
coaches and so on so forth lots of
things right so yes there is a there's a
lot of potential especially if you do it
if you do it with the multiple spots
so yeah
it can certainly work that way all right
let's see something else
some other questions
what's my take on marxism
marxism is a belief system just like an
abrahamic religion that's why
that's the kind of thing it is you know
marxism
okay so i i
marxism is an interesting thing
so in marxism you have
one prophet you have one book
and you have one god which is like there
is no god
and it's another dogmatic system
so it is certainly something that
merits
a certain amount of attention and study
because it has been so influential in
the past 100 or so years
it has taken a lot of lives and people
keep saying that it has never been
implemented properly
well who decides what marxism is
actually they say that you have not
implemented it properly and that's why
the economy was messed up or whatever
and that's why so many people died
that is kind of
not
very
true so i think i
should examine this in detail and by by
examining i mean i should create
a
dedicated video for that
that's what i should do so i'll put that
on my to-do list
raymond says i am a westerner studying
geopolitics and appreciate the indian
point of view my question is sri lanka
is
sri lanka considered the little brother
of india
is india involved in its current
economic issue
well if you look at the people of sri
lanka they look just like indians
the genetics are the same
the sri lankan there are two languages
spoken in sri lanka
sinalis and tamil both are
essentially indian languages
the culture is indian the religion two
religions again
if you consider buddhism separate from
hinduism so again these are indian
religions it's it's just
an extension of india if you look at the
history of sri lanka if you look at the
history of the sinali's people the
sinhalese people
their origin story is that they their
ancestors came from some part of india
they
were not quite sure where it was
most likely it was from kalinga the
eastern part of india present-day orissa
possibly from somewhere in saurashtra
that's another theory
so even the origin story is about
them coming from india and the tamil
people who live in sri lanka are
obviously of indian origin so clearly it
is nothing but an extension of india
same culture same people
similar languages and so on
so yes you could consider sri lanka to
be the little brother of india there
would be nothing wrong with that
with that i'm sure some sri lankans
would not like it well we don't mean it
in a demeaning way
so um
the other question is is india involved
in its current economic issue now india
has not created
the economic situation that sri lanka is
currently finding itself in
what's happened in sri lanka is horrific
mismanagement of the economy
by the
by successive regimes
the regime of
mahinda rajapaksa
in the 2010s onwards
from
from the middle of 2000 of the first
decade of the 2000s
then you have this guy called maitri
palas
sirisena
and then you have the rajpaksa family
again they have messed up the economy
beyond any limits right that's what
they've done
so india is involved right now in the
sense that india is trying to
bail out the sri lankans
india is extending these lines of credit
to the sri lankan government so that
they can acquire
things like fuel diesel or whatever to
generate electricity because right now
we are seeing all these blackouts in sri
lanka there's no fuel to generate
electricity and so on
and maybe we are sending food stuffs
food grains and all to sri lanka so
that's where india is involved right now
india has not created the issue
it is
the sri lankans their government
that has created the current economic
issue and even china is not really fully
to blame in this
the chinese did trap sri lanka in this
debt trap diplomacy which they do
everywhere
but
the contribution of that to the current
crisis is not as large as people believe
it is
the fault of the sri lankan governments
the various regimes
that's why the issue exists so uh
india is currently bailing sri lanka out
and the sri lankan government has
proposed a more integrated approach with
india that was tabled recently in the
past couple of years
so srila so
so we could have a more integrated uh
system with sri lanka obviously sri
lanka will remain a sovereign nation
but the politics will be to some extent
integrated the cultural uh
environments will be more integrated
there will be uh an integration of the
electricity grids of the two countries
and so on so forth so that's what we
could witness
in the coming
few years a more integrated
economy and other things between india
and sri lanka
which i think is a good move
why okay pratik asks why does the
scientific community
believe in the big bang
even though the laws of physics say that
something that exists can't come from
nothing and energy can't be created
just converted
well
what
is there in the laws of physics that is
against
that goes against the big bang theory
so what does the big bang theory say the
big bang theory is essentially the
history
of the universe based on what we know
about the laws
so it says that in the beginning
there was
a singularity or something very close to
a singularity a point in which all the
matter and energy of the universe was
concentrated and that somehow expanded
and that's what created the universe
so it's not like energy was created from
somewhere it was already there in that
little point
so that doesn't violate the conservation
of energy and we don't know what's
outside the universe if there is
anything outside
the laws of physics talk about what's
inside the universe that we live in they
don't say anything about what's beyond
the universe
so there is nothing
in the big bang theory that violates any
of the known laws of physics
so
it's not about belief
in science you don't believe something
you make observations you make
hypotheses theories and then you see
what works whether
the theory that you have made or
proposed whether it's able to explain
observed phenomena
and the best theory that we have as of
today is what is colloquially known as
the big bang theory
so that's what i can say my dear friends
according to imran khan
imran khan the u.s is trying to
overthrow his government
what's my take on this you know what
imran
it's not the u.s that's trying to
overthrow iran khan's government does
imran khan pose a threat to the us in
any way whatsoever
is he that powerful
imran khan has no power whatsoever he is
powerless
he is merely a puppet
of
the pakistani army
so if anyone is trying to overthrow
imran khan it would be the pakistan army
who actually runs the country who
actually owns the country
in the case of india
the country
has an army
the army belongs to the country and the
people of india the army serves the
country
and protects the people and the land
in the case of pakistan
the country doesn't have an army the
army is a country it's a small bunch of
people who own the entire country
and the people
so so these days so if you look at the
history of pakistan it's always been
military rule
you have elections from time to time
it's just i wash
you always have
the military that's really running the
show either overtly or covertly
so in the case of imran khan he is
simply a puppet
the election that he was elected in was
most likely a
rigged election
and even if it was not the army can
engineer whatever it wants
because they own the country they own
they have control over everything
and they have all the money
they have incredible amounts of money
stashed away somewhere or the other
and so
they don't want any
prime minister so-called prime minister
to stay in power for too long
because if any prime minister stays in
power for too long then they are able to
establish a political base that's how
politics works
so keep things
keep on changing things
use a revolving door policy one prime
minister for a little while than
somebody else for a different amount of
time and so on so forth
so um imran khan doesn't really have a
political base he's a cricketer in the
playboy
nawaz sharif was a bigger threat to the
pakistan army and you know what happened
to him
so imran khan is not that that big a
political player that he would pose a
real threat to the army so now they have
got rid of him right now imran khan is a
caretaker prime minister
and he is making various pronouncements
he's blaming
the us he's also blaming india i think
for overthrowing him
so
we don't need to take his
pronouncements his words very seriously
the real deal is the army the pakistan
army holds the real power in pakistan so
if anybody has overthrown imran khan is
the pakistani army
not the u.s
or not anybody else of course the u.s
does have a
certain amount of influence on the
pakistani army
they have always had the pakistan army
on their side
since the 1960s 70s onwards
recently the chinese have essentially
taken over pakistan to a large extent
but i hear nowadays these days in the
past few weeks
that the
pakistani army is again trying to woo
the u.s
maybe they feel a little threatened by
the proximity of the chinese
so let's see how that goes
will the americans be willing to again
start financing the pakistani generals
they also want india on their side right
the americans
so it's
it's right now up in the air but i would
say that imran khan
we don't have to take him seriously he
has never been a serious political
player he's never been a responsible
political player he's just a sock puppet
that's it
okay they just i will do it one of these
days
john ambrose says what about the paper
talk about the papers obtained by the
sun
from the pentagon about alien abduction
well i haven't seen the papers yet
but in the last couple of years the us
government and the pentagon in the
military
is is focusing on aliens these days
isn't it strange
for decades they denied
the
existence of aliens
ufos etc nowadays they're releasing
videos very grainy black and white
videos
of apparently what seems to be alien
ufos alien craft
and some other stories are coming out
it's very curious why they're suddenly
trying to focus on aliens
they're trying to create new threats out
of nowhere so
so i haven't read this report yet these
papers but i'm sure they'll make
interesting reading
as a kid i was fascinated with aliens i
hoped that aliens would exist and they
would come to
to our planet and we would get to meet
aliens and all that
but as far as i see today
i haven't seen any a single piece of
credible evidence
that there has been you know
incontrovertible evidence that there has
been an alien visitation to earth there
is plenty of
circumstantial evidence that
is intriguing
but there is no hard incontrovertible
evidence anywhere
of an alien visitation to earth
so what can i say i don't mind
an alien visitation i don't mind
meeting friendly green guys aliens or
girls whatever maybe they don't have
genders doesn't matter
but i have never seen that so
it's a childhood dream that has been
shattered
all right let's see what else we have
who is this naruto it's a japanese anime
isn't it naruto
naruto
never watched it i've heard a lot about
it
i hear it's very good and people love it
but i've never really watched it
unfortunately
and what's happening in the match 87 for
three
delhi capitals
and some old guys giving an interview
who is he
looks like an australian wearing an
indian dress whatever it is
and an australian bowler is bowling thai
who is thai
okay what else
deepak says can you please talk about
the gnostica schools of hinduism like
charvaka etc
so charvaka
is
materialism
materialism see when they make this uh
distinction between aztec schools and
gnostic schools what they mean
when they say nastic they don't mean
atheism
they may when when they categorize a
certain school of thought
as nastic
it means that
it denies the primacy of the vedas
the schools of thought that
recognize the premise of the vedas are
called the astik schools
and the schools of thought that deny or
reject the primacy of the vedas are
called nastic schools
so jaina dharma or the jaina school of
thought
does not recognize the primacy of the
vedas
and therefore
jaina
jaina jaina path is called a gnostic
path similarly
charvaka is a nastic part apart because
it denies the privacy
primacy supremacy of the vedas
now if you look at the various
philosophical schools of thought
that are under the
dharmic umbrella
you will see that the
what's the polite way of saying this
well the most superficial
of all of these is charvaka
charvaka is pure materialism it says
that whatever we see is the only thing
that exists
there is nothing
deeper or more profound to human
existence than the material world
there is no karma there is no
god the vedas are are false
and the only purpose in life
is to enjoy material pleasures
so that's all you should do
enjoy
the material world
so that's what charvaka says
i don't mean to demean this school of
thought or to demean any specific
individual
this is my personal perspective that's
how i see it
it is the
most superficial school of thought
within the dharmic umbrella
i would not even really call it
philosophy because there is nothing
philosophical about it of course it is a
certain worldview and some people will
say
some people will say but charvaka is the
scientific method
not quiet
not quite
the actual scientific method comes from
what is it i forget the atomistic school
of thought
of maharishi
which did believe in the
in the law of karma and all that
so this the scientific method came out
of other schools of thought from within
the dharmic umbrella not from charvaka
charvaka is just pure materialism so
that's what i can say in brief about
this
all right
raju says
do you watch anime or read manga
and if yes which one is your favorite
when i was a kid i used to love watching
cartoons which is nowadays called anime
but when you say anime i think you mean
japanese
cartoons right
so uh these days i don't have time to
watch anything like that or to read any
manga when i was a kid i love watching
cartoons
and some of those were japanese cartoons
what was it
no one will know them today
but yeah today i don't watch anime or
read manga but i used to be a huge fan
of all that when i was a kid but i never
really got the chance to
spend much time doing that
so today i don't know which which are
the which are the famous anime series or
manga i've heard of naruto
i've heard of
titan what is it clash of titan or
battle for titan or something
what is it called
not sure what it's called
and there is this other thing called uh
i forget the names i forget the names
okay someone is saying cartoon is
attack
attack on titan yeah that's right
and dragon ball z very good
and what else
yeah this one also i've heard of death
note
and somebody is saying cartoons are not
anime all right sir thank you very much
i am
educated now about this i do not know
that cartoons are not enemy so then
somebody answer this question for me
please what do you mean by enemy
if these animated cartoon series are not
enemy then what is enemy
when you say anime do you mean japanese
animated series what do you mean by that
what is one piece
maybe it's an enemy thing okay
[Music]
i'm so sad
um okay go going back to something more
serious
is white hunts and indian hunts
are these different of the same
uh
the horns were never indians but they
did settle down in india
and they did assimilate into the indian
population
the overall genetic influx from that
into indian india's population would
have been nothing more than a drop in
the ocean
so uh
during the gupta
empire during the gupta era of our
civilization
there were these multiple waves of
invasions by the shweta huna people
into india
so who are these peoples the peoples are
the ancestors of today's turks as well
as the mongols
the word hunu means human in the
mongolian language
so the ancient hudnik peoples
eventually gave rise
to the turkic ethnicity and also the
mongolian ethnicity now
when these shwetahunas were trying to
invade india
at the very same time they were also
busy invading the roman empire
they they they were mounting attacks on
rome itself
so they were spread all across eurasia
they were a nomadic people
so we in india for some reason we called
them the shwetahones i don't know why
they were shwetas why they were sweet
means white
so maybe there were white dresses or
they had white flags or maybe they had
white skin i don't know why why we
called them shivahunas
but that's what they were called
so they were foreigners they were
foreign nomadic people
they
mounted wave after wave of in attempted
invasions on india
the gupta emperor what's his name
what was his name
skanda gupta was it
most likely skandagupta if i'm not
mistaken i
i don't remember all the needs right now
but most likely it was kanda gupta
who repelled these multiple waves of
invasions
and
yeah it was kanda gupta not samudra
gupta samudragupta was a great conqueror
skanda gupta was the defender of india
so skanda gupta repelled wave after wave
after wave of hunnic invasion
he spent his whole life in the defense
of
the country
after he died
the horns succeeded to some extent
so the first conquered gandhar
which is now afghanistan
they settled down in afghanistan
they ruled gandhar they became hindus
and buddhists
they had
a couple of kings who were not good
for instance mihir akula was a very evil
guy no one liked him
mihir kul was a hunik king
and the reason he no one liked him is
because he oppressed
the both the people the buddhists
he oppressed the brahmanas he oppressed
everybody he was an atheist
so he was one of the evil kings but you
had other good kings also like torah
mana et cetera
kingila
who were reasonably good kings and they
all became they all became part of india
indian culture they married indians and
so on so after two three generations
they would look just like indians
so
and you had other ons who other honey
kings would
who were able to
establish kingdoms in northern india and
so on and so forth
so eventually they all became indians
after three four generations you would
not see any difference
between those who had hurnic ancestry
and those were indian ancestry
so
today you would have most indians who
would have some fractional ancestry from
those few homes
who entered india
1500 or so years ago
so that's what i can say about this
story
okay gnz gnz says how did ancient
indians look like
did they also
did they also have beards like the
greeks because i've never seen indians
portrayed with beards
you will see sculptures of gotham buddha
with beards
you would see chinese paintings of of
indian monks
with beards
and
i mean it's a biological thing
that males after the age of 13 14
whatever they
develop facial hair
so yes ancient indians would have had
beers i'm sure we had males
in ancient india i mean that's why they
exist right
uh this is good this is fun
yeah so yes we had beards yes our
ancestors had beards what did they look
like they looked like what we look like
today
score
so dc is a
i keep on thinking of deccan charges
it's delhi capitals it's one one zero
for three
exodus
who's batting let me see who's batting
who is batting rishabh bunt is batting
he's slashing the bat everywhere
and nothing is happening
and this australian guy i think
thai andrew thai is bowling and yeah
so that is what's happening in the ipl
beard sounds too much awkward
i suppose it may be awkward for some
people for some people it's
it's a personal choice whether you want
to have a beard or not you can
choose to be clean shaven if you like i
have never really grown a beard
in my entire life
maybe once when i was lazy for a month
or so but
nothing beyond that
pranjal says you are coming on prakhar
gupta's channel tomorrow what are you
thinking of discussing i don't know
whatever we whatever comes to mind
whatever he wants to ask me and whatever
we will see how it goes how the
conversation flows you don't go in with
a predetermined agenda
so whatever he wants to talk about we
will discuss let's see i'm sure it'll be
great fun
okay ishaan ishansh says is it in
india's interest to have a destabilized
pakistan
as it keeps our enemy weak or to have a
stable democratic pakistan as it may be
helpful in resolving issues or put a
pro-india government you know
we had people like what's his name ike
gujaral who was our prime minister for
three weeks or three minutes was it
three days
three years three months i don't know
what it was three months maybe
so this gentleman
shri ike gujaral let us address him with
respect
he said that his he had a doctrine but
he he made a doctrine of of his own with
his own name
he called it the gujarat doctrine
so according to this lofty gujarat
doctrine
india decided
that our neighbors should be stable
and we should have a strong stable
powerful pakistan and that was in our
best interest
and in accordance with this with this
so-called doctrine of his mr gujaral
he cut off all funding
to our intelligence assets within
pakistan and most likely they were
always exposed because of him
and
i'm assuming i don't have evidence of
this
but you can see lots of
commentary about this many articles have
been written
and most likely our intelligence assets
that we had developed over years over
decades were exposed and eliminated by
the pakistanis
right
so according to mr gujaral
it was in india's interest to have a
strong
stable pakistan
now
we just discussed pakistan some time ago
right
pakistan is owned by the pakistani army
and the only thing
that gives the pakistani army legitimacy
in the eyes of the alam the people
is the anti-india stance
the only thing that gives the pakistani
army legitimacy is the story the myth
that india is the big enemy
if india is not the enemy then there is
no need to have a powerful army right
so the reason for their existence is
this story that they create they keep on
creating that our big enemy is india and
they have given religious dimensions to
it and according to the religious dream
they want to take over india and convert
india into an islamic republic
so india essentially has to be conquered
and destroyed that is the gaza him or
whatever dream they have
so if that is the only reason for
existence
of pakistan
then should we
invest in a strong stable pakistan
pakistan is never ever ever ever going
to be a democracy
please understand this
repeat after me pakistan will never be a
democracy so then what is in india's
interest
what's in india's interest is no
pakistan
we would prefer it is better for us
to have a separate pashtun or maybe
pastor islam integrated with afghanistan
a separate sindh a separate balochistan
a separate punjab and then we can deal
with these guys
nicely properly in due time
and i'm not saying that india needs to
oppress them or conquer them or bomb
them or anything no
we should have good relations with them
but
we need to
disband the pakistani army in one way or
the other the pakistan army is the
biggest threat that we have to us it's
no longer a huge threat now
but it's a thorn in our flesh
and the thorn
is what other countries use against us
the americans used it against us for
decades
now the chinese are using it against us
so it is in india's interest to have
a balkanized pakistan
and hopefully without resorting to
violence i mean look at what the
americans did to the ussr they
balkanized the ussr without without
resorting to violence i appreciate that
great achievement
they broke the ussr without going to war
so one must commend what the americans
achieved
in in the early 1990s so let us draw
inspiration from our great american
friends
and
do the same to pakistan in the interest
of world peace and civilization
right so that is what is in india's
interest not a strong stable pakistan
and this idea of a democratic pakistan
it's it's just a dream
now when you're watching cricket you
should eat popcorn
so should i eat some popcorn i should i
don't like popcorn so i will eat grapes
how about that
[Music]
so we have a guy called aveshkhan who
has got seven wickets
good job sir
who gets in the whole ipl thus far
i heard about this
so aditya is saying who saw the full
interview between zelinski and arnab
i
was this today because i heard about it
today
arnab
yeah anyway i haven't i haven't seen it
yet
but i i perhaps will let's see
let's see what was discussed in that
okay mahakal mishra says
how to overcome mediocrity
it's not easy
mediocrity is like
the word mediocre means average it
doesn't mean that you're bad it means
you're average
how to overcome being average
by raising your standards
by not making compromises with quality
by increasing your discipline all of
this is hard and personal development
personal growth is really hard
it's very easy
to be like everybody else
but if you want to overcome mediocrity
then you have to
raise your standards raise your
expectations
have big dreams and try to work towards
that it's not easy it's very easy to
talk about it it's really really hard
but it's worthwhile
hmm
okay
mahul says is the universe expanding or
contracting it's expanding we know it's
expanding because when you look at the
galaxies from far far away
you see that they are all red shifted
which means all these spectral lines
of let's say whatever elements there are
oxygen nitrogen whatever they're all red
shifted they are shifted towards the red
end of the spectrum
not the blue end of the spectrum which
shows that they are going further away
and we also know that the
expansion is accelerating
okay
should we
should we uh consume grapes at night
i have been forbidden to eat fruits at
night
because
acid formation
may hamper the digestive system
some people have this problem of asylum
sorry i'm eating while speaking which is
very impolite i apologize
so
some people have this problem of acidity
now what is the uh most common cause of
acidity
i believe the most common cause of that
is too much consumption of carbohydrates
refined and processed carbohydrates like
a
processed wheat flour we call it maida
in india
so there are these digestive biscuits
that you get which are full of maida and
they say they are sugar free and good
for diabetics please
if you have diabetes and you kill this
and you eat these digestive biscuits
it's gonna kill you
so the thing is this
what causes acidity is not fruits
it is these refined
processed
carbohydrate-rich fruits
so
i uh not fruits foods i apologize foods
not fruits
so in my opinion i have never ever
experienced
acidity
or any such thing by eating fruits
day or night
i eat
okay
okay let's see some of the questions
what's happening in the ipl nothing is
happening all right
watson says
is the bactrian empire in the kushan
empire the same thing
um
bactria
is the greek name
for northwestern india
and there was no such thing as a
bactrian empire
it was bactria was
the greek name for a geographical region
of india
the region which is now
western punjab
and present day afghanistan
that is what the greeks called bactria
it was a part of india historically
so
there was no empire that emerged out of
this region
there were empires in india from time to
time you had as we know as we know as we
have discussed
you had the maurya empire the shunga
empire the kushan empire the gupta
empire
the
but none of these empires emerged out of
the geographical region
that the greeks called
bactria so the kushan empire
when it became an empire it's
it had two principal capital cities not
one two
one was i believe
mathura
in northern north northern india
and the other was
purushpur
which is now known as peshawar
which is in present-day punjab
right so um
so the kushan empire encompassed
most of the indian subcontinent and much
of central asia
from the aral sea to the caspian sea and
also
large parts of present day chinese
occupied xinjiang
it was a huge massive empire
and it was
constructed
through satya and ahinsa
well not quite it was constructed
through violence and conquest by the
great emperor kanishka
who was also one of the most dharmic
emperors our country has known our
civilization is known
he was a great
supporter of dharma
and he funded so much
so much of indian culture so so
in short to answer your question
there was no such thing as a backtrain
empire bactria was a region the kushan
empire was a whole different thing
now this is an interesting question mr t
says
do you think our indian indian engineers
are incompetent
as we have developed so much less
indigenous technology on any sector
we are often obliged to import foreign
technology
i think india's engineers are brilliant
i think india's engineers are the best
engineers in the world
unfortunately they are able to do their
best work when they work abroad
so why is it that an engineer who
appears incompetent in india suddenly
becomes a genius
in a different country why is it so it's
because of the indian system now people
blame the people of india
for the system
it's not the people of india who are to
blame for the system that is
ruling us
it is the transfer of power in 1947
that
continued the oppressive colonial system
of the british raj
it still continues today
and it's an oppressive system it's a
bureaucratic system the bureaucrats rule
over the people they lord or the people
you have this dynastic politics and so
much more so it is this incompetent
system the system of incompetence
that prevents indian engineers from
truly
flowering
so you have let's say you have an
organization like
let's name it
drdo
which has a very similar budget to the
american organization darpa
but this
american organization
has 150 employees
for a budget of about i don't know
2 billion dollars
150 employees or scientists or engineers
who have a budget of 150 off of two
billion dollars
in drdo we have a similar budget but we
have 30 000 employees
out of which there are only 5 000
scientists and engineers
so you can see the structure is such
that all the money will be wasted in the
wrong place on on
non-scientific people's
salaries
so where's the money for the science
and the engineering and when you don't
have sufficient money how will you do
anything how will you develop anything
of any consequence
so the system is to blame the
bureaucrats and the leaders are to blame
and hopefully now we are seeing changes
hopefully now we'll see changes drdo is
still run the same way
but you can see that we are doing so
much with such less money look at what
isro is achieving
look at what our scientists and
engineers were able to achieve
with the lca pages program once the
right government came into place
and so on so i think we have the best
talent in the world but we need the best
leadership to allow the talent to
to achieve its true potential
okay what else we have
so naina says what do you think about
circus it's almost wiped out from india
is it possible to revive it
yeah circuses were a thing of the past
weren't there i'm not sure if there are
any circuses today the problem is that
in today's world
we have
all of this all of these ott platforms
we have on-demand access to all kinds of
entertainment
so there's no need nowadays for people
to go to circuses
to move physically to this location in
this big tent and pay the entry fee and
spend two hours watching something that
is predetermined
you can just sit at home in front of
your big screen tv and you can keep
channel surfing you have 200 300
channels to choose from so
so that's why things like the circus and
other things have kind of died out today
it's just a consequence of the evolution
of technology and things
so i think it may be very hard for
people to revive circuses
a circus
would have any relevance if there is
money in it
but today
money is not there in things like that
so that's why it's not quite doing well
okay i am a little distracted because
there is this cricket match going on
here let's see what's happening
daily capitals 142 for three
18.3 overs only nine balls left
and aveish is bowling
and the rishab pant just hit a boundary
i think
did it reach the boundary yes it did
good job sir good job
okay let's see something
else other questions
somic says
can india not leverage
indian americans
against the usa
only a powerful country can do that i
mean a really powerful country
the chinese are able to leverage
chinese americans
against the u.s government
many american citizens of chinese origin
of chinese ancestry
are
known to be
acting as spies for the chinese
communist party
they are working in various
u.s organizations
whether it is uh
whether it is in engineering whether it
is in science and technology and they
whether it is in virology biology
and they have been many of them have
been caught
stealing
information secrets data
and transferring it to the chinese
communist party's
government
so why are these chinese doing it these
are chinese americans doing it first of
all because now they feel a sense of
pride in being of chinese origin
china is now a powerful nation
china is nearly
nearly a superpower to some extent it's
not quite a superpower it's not yet a
superpower but it's the biggest power in
asia
it is more powerful than russia it's a
it has a huge economy it has grown so
much
in the last 30 40 years
it is excelling in education in
technology and it has the funds
to buy people
and things like that right so there is a
certain amount of pride that chinese
that people of chinese origin have in
china
india still hasn't reached the stage
the state
where
indian origin people would feel proud of
india
right there is still so much
disinformation misinformation about
india
the first thing a person from the west
will think
when they hear the word india is caste
system
caste system this fake
creation of the british
so there is a sense of shame to some
extent
that indian americans have in being
indian they try to hide their indian
identity they never wear it on the on
their sleeve
so it is hard to leverage people
in that in that case when first of all
you don't have enough money
to buy them out to give them a better
alternative that if something goes wrong
in the u.s you can come back to india
and you will be taken care of and
secondly there is there is a lack of a
sense of pride in being indian
so the the solution is very simple like
i keep saying india's economy has to
grow
india needs to become at least a 10
trillion dollar economy
once it reaches that stage it india will
be a whole different beast
so as of today you find these indian
origin minions
who bark against india recently there
was this individual called the leap
singh or whatever
he is a member of the u.s government
right now he came to india and he
threatened india
that you need to do what we say
otherwise there will be consequences
that sort of thing
and you have all these indian origin
people who work in
who are in these big positions in the
u.s
the
boss
of google
is of indian origin the boss of
microsoft is of indian origin
now the acting boss of twitter
is of indian origin and there are many
such people
but
does it enhance india's influence in the
us
even one percent it does not
so india needs to change things up
and grow first
for this sort of
scenario to be possible
okay do we have
other questions
they just says do you think india needs
to spend more on information warfare
and pro-india media channels
yes
yes india does need to do that i don't
know why it's not happening
i suppose there must be some reasons why
it's not happening thus far
but india does need to do that
do you see india competing with the us
or china in quantum computing in 5 10 15
years
what would be an ideal population for
india considering the resources we have
in ai advancements
let me take the second question first
the ideal population for india is
considering the size of the indian
subcontinent
maybe a hundred million maybe 300
million
which is
today if you if you say that the ideal
population is 300 million
then today we have four times of that
nearly five times four and a half times
of that
so our population density is way way way
too high
the first question that we take now do i
see india competing with the u.s or
china in quantum computing
in between five to 15 years maybe in 10
years yeah possibly
the thing is
the americans and the chinese are like
10 20 years ahead of us
when it comes to quantum computing india
isn't even a super con super computing
superpower
we have the ability to develop and
design and create our own super
computers but we have never really
exploited that
if you look at the top 100 most powerful
super computers in the world
i think one or two in that list will be
indian
all the others will be american or
chinese
there will be one or two french
super computers maybe two three japanese
ones but it's mainly the us and china
now when it comes to quantum computing
again the americans have taken the lead
the chinese are following i'm not quite
sure what india is doing in this
why can't we have a competition
among the iits in other institutes like
that
every year a yearly competition who
builds the most powerful
super computer
quantum computer whatever
why can't we have a yearly competition
with proper big prize money
set aside a budget
of let's say
10 crores per year or 100 per year it's
a small amount for the government
let's say you set aside a budget of 100
crores per year
and give it to the entire team that wins
the contest on a yearly basis
imagine
[Music]
the kind of impetus it would give
to the development of of this technology
but we simply don't do it
so i hope this
changes
i hope it changes
so what do i see happening maybe in 10
years we may be somewhere on the scene
on the global scene when it comes to
quantum computing but we need to do that
all right um
so keshav says if pakistan is so corrupt
then why can't we buy them and
get it fragmented
pakistan is corrupt the politicians are
corrupt even the generals are corrupt
but the generals
want to hold on to this golden goose
that they have the golden goose is the
country
if the country is fragmented they will
lose whatever power
they have and they will lose whatever
sources of income they have
so they will not it is not in their
interest to allow the country to get
fragmented
so they will tolerate corruption they
are themselves corrupt
they are available
for purchase to the highest bidder
whether it is the americans the chinese
or both
but they will not allow the nation to be
fragmented because then it will make
them irrelevant
so that is why
pakistan is still unified because the
army needs it to be unified and because
a unified pakistan
has some value
to countries like the us
and china both of these countries
use pakistan as leverage
against india
from time to time in a variety of ways
so that is why currently we are
currently as of today
we are not quite yet in a position to
fragment pakistan
maybe in the future
for that india again has to grow
india has to get more powerful
ovasso agarwal says what's the
what's the reason the majority of women
keep long hair
while majority of men keep short hair
how did that start not sure
but traditionally indians
male
as well as female indians had long hair
shoulder length
this sort of thing
so i don't know how did this tradition
start
i believe even in other countries like
the so-called indo-european countries
in the past men used to have long hair
so i i
don't quite have the answer to your
question it's an interesting question
how did this
tradition or this custom start
that men should have short hair and
women should have long hair
not quite sure
but it's interesting i i
i think it is something that
one should look at is to understand how
these strange customs began
arabic says is it okay to believe that
the oldest civilization
started around the ganges ganga
might be the oldest one even before the
indus valley
due to low research of that region see
arkit first of all let me explain
there's only one civilization in india
there's not a separate ganga
civilization a separate indus
civilization a separate tamil
civilization a separate delhi
civilization a separate kolkata
civilization there is only one
civilization in india
and as far as we know
it is at least 10 000 years old why do i
say it's just one civilization because
you see the same culture everywhere in
different forms
different manifestations
of the same culture and there is
unbroken cultural continuity that goes
back 10 000 years
so it is just one civilization you have
different eras
and different phases of this
civilization so the so-called indus
valley or harappan era was one era or
one phase
of this unbroken 10 000 year old
indian civilization
so what happened what you find in the
ganga valley region
is not a separate civilization
it is a ganga valley local
manifestation
of india's civilization
if you find something in the sindh
region
along the so-called indus valley or the
saraswati valley
or any other valley that is a local
manifestation of indian civilization
so we don't know
we don't quite know how old our
civilization is
from the archaeological record we know
that it is unbroken for at least nine
and a half or ten thousand years
but we have done
no real archaeological work in the ganga
valley
and even along the saraswati valley
and there are so many places that we
know
there are archaeological sites there but
we have not explored them so as we start
doing that the antiquity of our
civilization
that we have evidence of will increase
so we don't know where it began
did it begin in the ganga valley did it
begin in the saraswati valley did it
begin in the yamuna valley or somewhere
else we don't know we still don't have
evidence
so
we we don't go as per
we don't go on the basis of belief
we go on the basis of hard evidence
so based on that hard evidence the
oldest
evidence that we have
is from the saraswati region
the village of virana in haryana
that is the oldest known
archaeological site in india
it's about nine and a half
thousand years old
so that is where you find the oldest
evidence thus far of indian civilization
and you see cultural continuity
that dates back to that time
right so it's just one civilization we
don't have 75 different civilizations in
india we have only one civilization
that's what i can say
okay so now it seems there is a break in
the ipl innings break
so who scored what i have kind of lost
track of it
so delhi capitals made
149 for three only three
all right that's the innings break
okay let's see some other questions yeah
yeah yeah aliens
so avinash says how was the kailash
temple built in maharashtra
was it alien technology or our own
so the question i would like to ask in
response is do we have any evidence
any incontrovertible evidence
of aliens visiting this planet
do we
the answer is no
so if there is no evidence anywhere on
our planet
when i mean evidence i mean hard
evidence
there is no such evidence
that if there is no evidence of aliens
then how can we claim that or believe
that it was alien technology
the
simpler answer is that it was human
technology it was our own technology
so there is this uh
there is this view that people have
it this the the origin of this
view
is from the west
so the western world view is that the
past was primitive the present is
advanced and the future will be even
more advanced
so human beings who lived 500 years ago
were more primitive than us today
our ancestors who lived 2000 years ago
were way more private primitive than
what we are today
so the world view of the west is that if
you go back in the past you go back to
primitive times
but
maybe in the case of india
in some ways in certain ways maybe we
were more advanced in the past
so it's possible
that we had better
that our skills
in chiseling rock in carving rock and
carving out entire temples out of a
single block of rock
was
something that was way more advanced at
the time and we have kind of lost that
skill today
so i believe i mean for me it's very
clear there was no alien technology
involved in this
for me it's very clear it was indian
it was the skill of the indian craftsmen
and artisans maybe crafts women i don't
know
so it is that
that allowed us to build this
temple
oh okay shylander says will you try to
join politics no sir no thank you no
plans
i i don't know what how politics works
all right
is it true that nehru
awarded himself
the bharat ratna it is true yes
it is true
the great man he he was so great
he was so great he awarded himself the
greatest
the greatest prize
that india has
i mean how many people can do that
okay let's see some other questions
so luck now needs 150 runs to win
and that will be soon i suppose
okay
master hitesh says
from where can we learn about ancient
indian culture
did the mughals distort hindu scriptures
the mughals distorted in those
scriptures
the turks destroyed all our libraries
and universities
and the the europeans
distorted our history even further
they tried to re-engineer our society
and they wrote their own falsified
history of india of india's civilization
and
and culture
so where do you learn about ancient
indian culture you have to try and look
up authentic sources
the best way to do it is to
is to learn sanskrit but it's obviously
something i cannot ask everybody to do
so then you read translations of various
books and you do find some good authors
some reliable authors and all
for me what's worked is that i read a
lot i'll read a lot of books a lot of
research papers lot of articles
and from all of that voluminous amount
of information
i
get a sense of what is written what's
wrong that's how it's worked for me
so people ask me give me one book that i
can read
to learn about indian history i don't
have an answer to that
every single book i have read
has some distortions
every single book i have read has some
falsifications of indian history
the problem i face is that when people
ask you to recommend a book i know that
when i recommend x y or z book there is
going to be some misinformation in that
especially when it comes to things like
the so-called aryan invasion of
migration of india which never happened
but every single book even by good
authors even really good books that i
know about even these good books
have this misinformation whether it is
rc majunder whether it is
basham
or anybody else
they all have these
distortions so what do i do how do i
recommend a good book
the best way is to read lots and lots of
books
and then slowly over time you will form
your own patterns
but obviously that is very hard to do
so maybe i'm going to have to write my
own books
maybe then you will get the answers
let us see
okay next question
it is by kaushal
will the chinese communist party crumble
eventually and will china fall down
if not then the ccp will be in power for
the next few decades
and then can india and the us be true
friends
all right
so
i must have said this before let me say
it again
there are no friends
in geopolitics
true friends or even false friends in
geopolitics there are temporary allies
and temporary adversaries
in some cases you may have
long term or even or even permanent
adversaries if you share common borders
because you cannot
solve the problem of geography
so
there can never be friends or true
friends in geopolitics
right first please understand that
i would say read the arthashastra if you
want to really understand how
geopolitics works it tells you
everything
national interest is about self-interest
so if you say that a so-and-so nation is
your friend it means that our interests
align
currently
so
so the question you are asking is will
the ccp crumble eventually
yes
eventually the ccp will crumble
when you say ccp you mean the chinese
communist party
eventually it will crumble this
phenomenon is called the dynastic cycle
so if you look at the history of china
uh chinese history is about
two and a half three thousand years old
if you want to be charitable you can say
it's about three and a half thousand
years old so if you look at the overall
history of china there is this
phenomenon that you see
which is known as dynastic cycles a
dynasty rises emerges
becomes strong
reaches its pinnacle
and then it crumbles
because of because it becomes
well the kind of thing take things
for granted and so on
and then the dynasty crumbles and then
you have a period of about a century or
two centuries of chaos and then a new
dynasty emerges
and when i say dynasty i mean imperial
dynasties so so the chinese communist
party is the latest
imperial dynasty
in china
they don't have dynastic succession
but it is still a kind of a dynasty
so it is
a new manifestation of a dynastic cycle
and eventually even the chinese
communist party will crumble
maybe in the next 10 years maybe in the
next 100 years we don't know yet
but
it will eventually happen
now when will it happen
i cannot tell you
i am not nostradamus i don't see the
future
one hopes that we will be able to solve
our problems with the chinese and the
only way
india and china can resolve the problems
is if tibet becomes free
as long as we have a chinese communist
party soldiers on our borders
india and china will never have
true
peace and never we will never have good
relations with each with each other
so
and when it comes to the us
the u.s as long as it's a powerful
nation it's going to keep bullying india
the us is by nature a bully that is the
kind of track record they have with
everybody
so they are even
in the habit of bullying the uk
there is something i have never spoken
about have i
if you look at the history
of the relations
between the u.s
and the uk in the post-second world war
world
then you will see that it's
a relationship that is based on bullying
the us has always in the past 78 years
bullied the uk
and
sometimes it worked sometimes the uk
would resist that especially when you
had a strong prime minister like
margaret thatcher
which is when relations were not very
good
and then we had somebody like tony blair
who was essentially an american lap dog
and then you had the same thing yeah so
so the u.s is essentially by nature a
big bully
so india and the us
can never be
like you say
true friends
there is
an asymmetric relationship
there is a stark power asymmetry
when it comes to the relationship
between the us and any nation
including india
so the chinese communist party
complicates the matter of obviously
uh please disabuse yourself of this
notion of friends
there are no friends in geopolitics
people say israel is india's great
friend come on
our interests currently align
to some extent with the interests of
israel that's why we have good relations
but i can promise you
that the israelis are also spying on
india
and maybe the indians are also spying on
israel that's how it works in
geopolitics
all right
what else do we have what else do we
have
samarth says can you explain the entire
history
entire history of the yemen conflict
which is not being reported by
media
who is benefiting from this war and
trying to prolong it al-qaeda
al-qaeda
what is al-qaeda
it's a proxy
used by somebody
to achieve some certain objectives
all right
so let's not go into who is using this
proxy who created the proxy what the
objectives are
let's not go there right now
the entire history of the yemen conflict
goes back several centuries
it's not possible to explain it right
now but if you want to learn about what
happened and what what
is the root cause of this conflict
uh please refer to my interaction my my
podcast with dr issa bloomy on this
channel
it's like a two-hour plus conversation
in which he goes
into great detail about the situation in
yemen about the history
about who is
the principal
driver
of this conflict who is benefiting from
it
and so on
so that's what you should look at if you
want to understand what's really
happening
in yemen you are right the media will
not speak about this
whether it's the western media or the
indian media that's why i went ahead and
spoke with dr isla sabloomi because he
is someone who has
written about this extensively he knows
about this conflict
so if you want to understand what's
really happening there please check out
that
podcast episode on my channel
pranjal says any update on rakhigarhi
and the dr nirajara's dna work thus far
no
hopefully
hopefully soon and when i say soon maybe
this year maybe next year
by the time i expect that this
new research paper will be published the
one about r1a1a or r1a
so that's what we are waiting for that
is something that's very
eagerly awaited and anticipated by
everybody
uh my views about nostradamus
predictions for bharat
i had read about uh notre dames and his
predictions uh
i don't know maybe long time ago
more than a decade ago after that i've
not read about it
so what were his predictions for india
i think he said that india would become
a superpower in the 22nd 21st century
some
great leader will emerge in india
and so on so that's what i remember kind
of vaguely
about what
nostradamus had said
so let's see if it comes true
i don't know
if if he if that's what he said then i
hope it comes true
so that's what i can say about this in
brief
so once again we're dealing with aliens
aliens
himadri shekhar gupta says please shed
light on the sun newspaper
they have obtained new declassified
documents about alien encounters where
they have impregnated five women
if this is true this is massive news
you know the sun
this newspaper called the sun is what's
known as a tabloid
uh
they indulge in
sensationalism
their front page is usually an extremely
sensational story
and much of it is often to be understood
that it's not quite
quite 100 factual
so i i i haven't read this first of all
but it's the kind of story that you
would expect
uh the sun to publish
now um so i don't know how much
factual this is what is the origin of
the story maybe the americans are
releasing these stories to them to the
media
so i don't know but what is the evidence
if this claim has been made what is the
evidence
show me the evidence
the evidence has to be hard evidence
incontrovertible evidence
evidence that cannot be refuted
thus far i have never seen a single
piece of evidence of any alien activity
on this planet
so i am extremely deeply skeptical about
this
that's what i can say
tanmay says it was houston stewart
chamberlain
who was a proponent of the aryan
dravidian theory and caste system he
said that aryan reyes got weak after
marrying non-aryans
do you know about it breaking india book
no i'm not quite sure if i've come
across this name houston stewart
chamberlain but yes it is quite your
the broad point that you're making is
absolutely right that it is these
foreigners
who have been making all these claims
they have appointed themselves
as the experts
about india's history
i mean you know it's an assault on
india's history
it is an assault on the history of any
group of people
when history is not presented by the
elders of that group
when a bunch of foreigners comes
and appoints themselves to be the
custodians of your history
it is an assault on your
history on your culture and on your
civilization
a nation's history
should only be presented by the elders
of that nation
otherwise it's an it's an assault on
your history it is an attempt to
colonize your nation
all right
um what else do we have
i am confused what i want to do after
class 12.
can you help me as i am pressurized by
my parents any advice
see i i don't know you personally i
don't know your background so it's
really hard to
give any specific advice
what i would say is that
is that you have to ensure
that
you are financially
independent as soon as possible
this is
something that every youngster needs to
remember
you need to become financially
independent at as soon as possible
so maybe it's at the age of 17 18 i mean
once you are 18 you're you're legally an
adult
so whatever career path you take
you have to first ensure financial
independence
once you are financially independent you
have choices
if you are financially dependent on
anybody let's say your parents or
anybody else you don't have much of a
choice in your life right
so the first thing is to be practical
and to become financially independent
and then hopefully you should have a
career that is in line with your
aptitudes and your in your
and and whatever your interests are so
for that you have to understand yourself
properly most people unfortunately are
confused because they don't understand
themselves
our education system is such that
you never have the time
to spend on your own
maybe two three hours every day alone
trying to understand who you are
you will never understand who you are
by memorizing nonsense from textbooks
by obeying your teacher or whoever else
to understand to truly understand
yourself you need to spend time with
yourself alone
without
the interfering presence of anybody else
but as kids we don't get that at all
we don't even get one or two hours a day
to go and play outside
all you do today
is class work school work homework
tuitions
and expectations
so that's why people are confused
so um
so it's hard it's hard
so you need to somehow
find some time
to understand yourself then you will
know what your aptitudes are what your
likes and dislikes are and hopefully you
can find a career that is in line with
that but before you do any of that you
need to ensure that you become
financially independent as soon as
possible
that is the practical part of the advice
that i would give so that's what i can
say in in
in general
rishi says what's your take on
anti-india propaganda developing in
bangladesh
it says that it was
it says it was the bangladeshis who
liberated the land and india took away
their credit why this hate
it's what their education system teaches
them
the bangladeshi system education system
teaches the kids that it was the mukti
bahini who fought the war and who
liberated bangladesh and
at the last minute the indian army came
enrolled into dhaka and took and and
stole all the credit from the bukti
bahini
that's what the bangladeshi kids are
taught for the past 30-40 years
so that's why they hate india
they are told that it was their
greatness that liberated bangladesh from
pakistan and india is the one who has
tried to take away the credit
and obviously there are the other angles
too let's not go there so that's why the
bangladeshis feel this way
it's propaganda it's lies
the mukti bahini
i don't want to disparage them i don't
want to demean them but here's the fact
the mukti bahini was a group of ragtag
half naked
bangladeshis
who were supported by india they were
trained by india they were given arms
and ammunition by india
and still they were not able to do
anything
all they were doing for months was
getting killed
they were not able to prevent the
pakistani genocide of the managing
people of the bengali people
was the mukti bahini able to prevent the
pakistani genocide of 5 million
bangladesh bengalis i don't know what
the real number is whether it's 1
million or 5 million maybe somewhere in
between
definitely more than 1 million people
were killed
and much worse was done by the pakistani
army
was the mukti bahini able to stop that
so what claims are they making
the mukti bahini was a bunch of ragtag
half naked losers
they were brave
but they were losers they were losing i
said they were losers because they were
losing
if we had
if the mukti bahin if the indian army
had not gone into pakistan even today
the mukti bahini would be trying to
fight
the pakistanis
right
so it is the indian army that liberated
bangladesh from pakistan the only
question is why did we not
reintegrate places like the chittagong
hill tracts with india
which would firstly have given india
uh the northeastern part of india the
far east of india access to the ocean
and secondly the chittagong hill tract
is a place where you have
hindus and bengali and buddhists who are
in a majority not the muslims it should
never have been part of east pakistan it
should never have been allowed to be to
remain a part of bangladesh but we gave
it up to bangladesh and today you have
all these terrific terrible
atrocities
that are being carried out by the
bangladeshis
in the chittagong hill trucks
region
forcible
demographic re-engineering
so
they that this is a complex issue
but the mukti bahini was like
if even if they had been fighting until
today they would not have been able to
liberate bangladesh
thing is very simple
if you want to fight
the state of pakistan you need arms
ammunition funding food supplies all of
that where were the mukti bahini getting
that
they were getting it from india
and despite that they were able to make
no headway because there were a bunch of
ragtag civilians
with no they did not have proper
military training they did not have any
of that so eventually it was the indian
army that had to step in and they did a
brilliant job of liberating bangladesh
and saving the people of bangladesh from
the pakistani monsters unfortunately the
pakistani monsters were not made to pay
for their crimes
of genocide and worse
so one has to blame
[Music]
whoever was in charge
of the situation at the time
okay what else do we have
not quite sure what's happening in the
match
let's see
any thoughts on the brown sepoy the leap
doing saber or rattling in india
and now the u.s doubling down on that is
this how allies behave the us is not
india's ally
the india the the us does not seek an
alliance with india
they sir they seek a master servant
relationship
that's what they seek
the americans are very clear any
relationship they have with anybody
is going to be a deeply unequal
a deeply asymmetrical relationship
they will be the masters
and their so-called allies will actually
be their servants the subsidiary
so that's what they seek they seek
deference and they seek essentially a
colonial status
which is what they have with germany
with much of western europe with the uk
with australia with new zealand with
japan with korea south korea and so on
so they seek a similar kind of
relationship with india and what better
way of doing it than sending a brown sea
poi to india a person of indian origin
who speaks the white man's language
so they sent this guy dalip singh
whoever he is never heard of him before
until recently he's some official that
they have
so they usually you use
somebody of the local ethnicity to go
and threaten or to go and bully or to go
and
interfere for instance with with
afghanistan they had this individual
called zalmai khalilzad
so zalmai khalid khalilzad
special
representative for afghanistan or
whatever new designation they treated
for him
a deeply corrupt individual
who presided over the destruction of
afghanistan for 20 years zalmai khalil
and now we have this guy called dalip
singh
who they have sent to who they had sent
to threaten india
so uh
no surprise there
that's what they do so remember all of
these guys all of these indian origin
people who live in the us they serve the
us they are not indians lots of indians
have this pride
that our guys our citizens our people
are
doing well in the u.s the question is
very simple that you ask yourself
who do they serve
whose national interest to the serve
whose national interest do they promote
and further
it's very clear that they are serving
the american national interest
so those are some of my thoughts about
dilip singh and this entire episode and
please understand the us is not an ally
of india
they do not see india as an ally
they seek to be india's masters
this is a neocolonial enterprise
what is a superpower
a superpower is an empire
it's just a new word for the old term
which is empire
the u.s is currently running an empire a
global empire
it has a
superpower status which means that it
can
intercede anywhere
in the world
at 30 to 60 minutes notice
which is
the sign of an empire of an imperial
system
so we are dealing with imperialism
here
pankaj says mumbai city fc is going for
afc champions league support them as
as well sure great
so when you say mumbai city fc you mean
football club right
and afc champions league means asian
football clubs champions league
that's what i expect it means
sure if they have if they have reached
that stage it's good
and we should support them
okay let me see what's happening to lsg
lsg means lucknow super something
what's the name lucknow supergiants
so there are 30 for no loss after 4.1
overs
and there is mr decock
who's batting
and uh
and kl rahul sorry about that
so
and who's bowling a south african guy
and rick northje
i don't know how to pronounce his name
say
it's a western name it's a dutch name
so that's what's happening
when it comes to the ipl and four runs
again
so that's all you see in the ipl fours
and sixes
okay okay okay
okay i get it
so
well savvy
decock
quentin let's call him quinton
harsh says the ruble has appreciated a
lot
will we see the usd devalued and see
unrest in the u.s because of this
combination of these factors
like food shortage currency devaluation
inflation and so on
uh the ruble has appreciated a lot and
what's happened there
how did that happen how did the russians
pull it off i mean the ruble is now
stronger
in
april 2022 as compared to what it was in
february when the
intervention in ukraine began so how did
they manage to strengthen the ruble
despite the bucket load of american
sanctions that have been dumped upon
them
that
is an interesting story
so let me not go into that right now
just just i'm just telling you i'm just
pointing this out that it's very
interesting the russians have have been
able to do that to pull that off
and while the ruble
is appreciating
the us dollar is depreciating
so that's what you the russians have
done
it is
very interesting and now you you're
right you're seeing things like food
shortage and inflation in the us it's
going to happen
so
will we see unrest in the u.s
[Music]
most likely not
because they know how to control their
population they know how the mind works
and they have the
monopoly of power
so i don't see
too much of unrest
in the u.s coming up
but what's really interesting is the
situation
vis-a-vis the ruble in the u.s dollar
the ruble is appreciating i suppose i
expect it may continue to appreciate
in the coming
weeks and months
okay this is interesting
are you familiar with satguru's save
soil movement what's your opinion on
that
unfortunately i am not familiar with it
i've seen this hashtag a lot
save soil but i have not had the time or
the chance to
to uh
go deeper into it and try and understand
what what it means
so
maybe that's something i should do but
thus far i don't have an opinion on that
because i i'm not
well informed enough
audral singh chaudhary says my question
is can you explain the difference in
similarity between three abrahamic
religions islam christianity judaism
so judaism is the first abrahamic
religion the oldest one the prophet
abraham was
the prophet of the jews
yeah and uh
then you had christianity which was uh
an
offshoot of judaism
so
the prophet of christianity is obviously
jesus jesus christ
who was obviously born a jew
and what's the difference between
christianity and judaism
different books i suppose
the belief system is very
similar it's about which which prophet
you hold to be the the true prophet the
greatest prophet in judaism you had a
number of prophets which are all
uh claimed by christianity to be
prophets of christianity as well
so there is actually very little
difference between judaism and
christianity obviously christianity has
a
uh
christianity is organized along military
lines
and uh
they have a centralized system
which judaism does not have
so practically it is implemented
differently
so judaism is more decentralized
christianity has this monolithic
military style structure which i believe
even islam has
and even when it comes to islam they
have
a newer prophet
uh prophet muhammad who they claim is
the last and final and true prophet of
of the world i believe
and they have their own book the quran
and they also claim that the various
prophets of judaism and christianity
are also prophets of islam but
but prophet muhammed is the final
prophet of
of the people of the book essentially
so these are some of the similar
similarities and differences in brief
obviously it's very complicated
but that's what i can say in very brief
because i am not quite to be very frank
an expert in the abrahamic religions i
have never studied them in depth
so that's what i can say in brief
says how do we argue or debate with a
person
with leftist mentality
based on facts
any argument any debate
has to be based
in fact
the problem with
see i have nothing against people with a
leftist outlook or mentality
most people who identify themselves as
leftists
are brainwashed
into this ideology by the education
system by their professors by the media
and so on
and
the thing about the leftist ideology is
that it uses the right words
it says that we are liberals
despite being some of the most ill
liberal and intolerant people in the
world
they call themselves liberals so they
have they have co-opted all the good
words for themselves
so it makes this this path very
attractive for a lot of people
especially when you're young when you
are easy to influence
it's easy to brainwash with that
and the leftist method of argument or
debating
is
very strange
they only have one real argument which
is character assassination
they never argue based on facts
they will either come up with distorted
facts or lies or misrepresent
misrepresentations
and when you challenge them challenge
them with real facts they will attack
your
character
it's called character assassination
it'll say you're a bad person and that's
why you have to be wrong that's why
whatever arguments you are making
cannot stand because you are evil
because you are bad
maybe because you're a hindu you're a
hindus that's why any argument that you
make
is invalid
that sort of thing that's the kind of
arguments that they have
so the best way to deal with leftists is
don't argue with them don't debate them
what's the point what will you get out
of it
what will you get out of debating a
leftist
so i personally have never really gone
into that i don't know the time or the
inclination to go and debate with people
who will not even debate factually
argue actually it's a pointless waste of
my time and energy
please understand you have a limited
amount of time
at your
disposal so use it wisely
okay lsg is 48 for no loss 5.1 overs mr
quinton is batting
and the bangladeshi bowler is bowling
what an interesting name
mustafizur
is a lefty
somitra says can the u.s use australia
against india in the far future as the
us is trying to give nuclear power
submarine
well if india u.s relations don't
progress the way the americans want
then they may use anybody against india
they used pakistan against india for
decades
they don't need to go so far as to as
so far east as australia
that they can use india's own neighbors
against india
they have used pakistan in the past they
can use them again
all they have to do is give a few
billion dollars in bribes to the
generals
and then the generals will do whatever
the americans want them to do
the pakistani army the pakistani
generals are always
for sale
to the highest bidder
right now they are in the chinese camp
but i hear i hear
that they are again interested in the us
for some reason
so they are hoping
that their american daddies will come
back to them
and
so if the americans want to use some
nation against india they have
ready-made
alternatives they have pakistan
they could even use bangladesh
if they need to
if they can give the right amount of
bribes or whatever
so the u.s has also used checkbook
diplomacy in the past
and as we know
maybe some of you don't realize it
the pakistanis
indulged in
terrorism against india for several
decades
they used terrorism as a state policy
from the um
from the 1980s onwards
until until now
even now when you have all these
encounters in kashmir
it is
the indian army
encountering terrorists
that have come across the border from
pakistan
so pakistan still uses terrorism as a
state policy against india
now in the 1980s and 1990s
and in the early 2000s also
pakistani terrorism
was financed
by the united states
so the u.s
was financing
pakistani terrorism in india pakistan
was a proxy
the real
agent
or perpetrator
or orchestrator of the terrorism
was the u.s
so um
so yeah they could they could do it
again in the future
if they want to
if they want to teach india lesson for
whatever reason or something
so yeah there are multiple alternatives
that the us has if it wants to do
something like this
ranjal pandey says your views on rc
majumdar's books on history
are they accurate and reliable see it's
very simple
these books
were written almost a century ago
so the information they have
is antiquated
information
that's
you could you could consider that
information to be a century old
now in the
in the century that
came after the publication of these
books
a lot more
information and data
is now available
and we
have
a much better understanding of indian
history
so
when we look at advances in archaeology
when we look at new archaeological
discoveries when we look at the advances
in the science of genetics and what it
tells us about history none of that is
obviously going to be there in the books
of rc majumdar
and yet
those books are very good
so you have to understand that there
will be some
outdated
ideas in those books
outdated information in the in the books
for instance those books if i recall
correctly the he speaks about the aryan
invasion theory as if it was a fact
so when he wrote those books
the aryan invasion theory was
uncritically accepted universally by
everybody as a fact
all indians believe that this is what
happened
today we know
better
so what i would say is that those books
are still very good
written very well lots of good
information there but you have to also
know
that some of this information is going
to be outdated
so i would still consider the rc
majunder books as good
they are still a very valuable source of
history historical information
but they are
in some portions
outdated
that's what i can say
okay this what's your view about kumari
condom it doesn't exist
there is zero evidence for any
sunken
continent
south of india none whatsoever
thoughts on ms dhoni
he used to be he's one of our greatest
cricketers
very aggressive batsman good uh
wicketkeeper okay captain but he used to
lead from the front
so yeah one of the greatest of all
indian cricketers one of the greatest of
all indian sports people and he still
plays which is interesting
so that's my thoughts about him
he suddenly uh
made the indian cricket team more
aggressive and brought out an aggressive
more aggressive
um form of india you could say you know
so it was a good change
pratishwar says you have educated us on
the topic of power and leaderships a few
times now
can you please expand further on this
topic
people say money is power but is money
really power
money is currency
now
you can use currency to expand your
power base
if you are powerful enough you can use
money to
to further your influence to acquire
more power
but if you are powerless and you have
money
then that money is going to be stolen by
somebody else who has more power than
you
so uh
so leadership
is something that
is possible
with power
if you have the leadership qualities
but you
don't know
the secrets of power
how to leverage power how to wield power
then your leadership
skills are
going to be pointless
so the understanding of power is
actually
integral
to being a good leader
and
power comes from leverage
power comes from people who will obey
you the more people you have who will
obey you the more powerful you are
power is not influence
power is obedience
so that's
something politicians understand
all political power comes from street
power especially in countries like india
you know that
that's why um
so that's how it works so this is a
complicated topic maybe i should do a
dedicated video on that
so money is not power money is power
when you are already powerful then you
can use money to buy more power to a
certain extent
so
power leadership money these are all
tied together intricately
it's a nice
triangular tango you could say
so
i
i will take this up and maybe make a
separate dedicated video or session
about this
okay so what's the deal here oh there's
a break going on
so lsg is 51 for no loss
in uh how many hours
in seven hours and kale rahul has made
12 runs in seven hours
amazing
so it is the other guy what's his name
quinton
who is doing well good for him
all right
okay tanya says can you please explain
where does the name india come from
the name india comes from the indus
river
the indus river
is what the greeks called the sindhu
so the sindhu is the indian name of that
river that great river which is our
river our civilized it's one of our
civilizational rivers
and truly speaking
india
as a culture
and as a civilization is incomplete
without ownership of this of the sindh
river
so that is unfinished business for india
reclaiming the entire sindhu river
india will be incomplete
as long as the sindhu river
is not
part of india
so so that's a digression but the name
india comes from
the sindhu river which the greeks called
indus
our persian cousins called it the hindu
river because saw becomes her in the
language
and that's how this term hindu came
about
okay
john jonas says how powerful is the
iranian army i am iranian
the iranian army is as powerful as
see the question is how powerful
is a nation's army
your army is
the power of your army is typically
proportional
to the power of your economy
so if you have a one trillion dollar
economy hypothetically
the you may spend maybe
two percent or five percent of your
economic
of the of the economy
on
the
budget of the armed forces
so if your
gdp
is let's say one trillion dollars per
year
you may spend about
about 50 million dollars
per year sorry billion
something like that maybe 50 billion on
the army if you are spending five
percent of the gdp
if your
gdp is 10 trillion dollars you may be
able to afford to spend 500
billion dollars so the power of your
army is directly proportional to the to
the strength and the size of your
economy
so what is the size of the iranian
economy let me do a very quick search
iran gdp
what's the gdp of iran
so it is
in dollars in dollars
it is
19.171 crores
dollars how do you convert crores to
billion
10 crore is 1 billion
yeah i'm kind of confused over here
i always get confused between crores and
lakhs and billions and millions
so the gdp
is
iran is 19 greece is 18 turkey is 72. so
iran's gdp let me just say this is is
quite small unfortunately compared to
other countries for instance it is like
one
almost one-fourth
of the gdp of turkey
now if you look at the army of turkey
it's not a very powerful army
it's like a it's like a local regional
power
so iran's
army would get
less funding
maybe a fourth or quarter of the funding
that the turkish army would get and of
course there are all these economic
sanctions on iran
so i would say that the iran iranian
army is very powerful internally it
knows how to control the iranian
population and keep the current regime
in power it is able to do that it has
an iron grip on the internal
um
on the internal systems and everything
but when it comes to fighting off
external aggressors
it may not be that powerful when it
comes to let's say one of the biggest
neighbors that iran has is saudi arabia
it is also one of iran's biggest rivals
and the saudi arabians they have an
enormous military budget
it's in excess of 50
billion dollars per year
and they don't they do it obviously to
keep the americans happy
so i think there is a significant
asymmetry power asymmetry budget
budgetary asymmetry when it comes to the
saudis and the iranians
so um
iran is definitely
a genuine
regional power
i would say
the conventional strength of the iranian
army would be greater than that of
pakistan
maybe even greater than that of the
arabs
because the arabs haven't
don't have the greatest
military traditions
the iranians the persians have always
been an imperial power in the past 3000
years of history
so
they have a good military tradition
but because of the financial and
budgetary constraints
they may not quite be very powerful
today
but they do aspire the iranians do
aspire to become an empire again a great
power again
and that's why they are trying
to acquire
and develop nuclear weapons
so that is what i can say sir
all the best to iranians i mean
you guys are our cousins
we always had good relations with you in
the past
unhc suspended russia really
i hadn't
heard of that
so let me we will look into that if that
has actually happened what is unhc maybe
you mean sc
dungar singh chauhan says any thoughts
on peter francisco who is that
let me see who is peter francisco
haven't heard of him p.e
peter francisco
american soldier
interesting
so see the there you found a topic that
i haven't heard of have i heard about
so
so obviously since i have not
read about this gentleman
i would not have any thoughts about it
but i will read this up
maybe next time i could answer the
question
varun says do you ever get an
extraordinary spiritual
experience when gazing at stars
because i always get that experience you
know i
as a kid i used to
spend hours
gazing at stars
i never got a spiritual experience or
some
anything that i would call a spiritual
experience but i used to really love it
enjoy it i used to
lie flat on my back and i used to
watch gaze at stars for hours and
i used to wonder what was going on up
there
so who else who else is out there you
know
because i'm quite sure that alien
civilizations and life forms must exist
around other star systems and i used to
wonder about that so it's a very
peaceful calming experience your
thoughts go in all kinds of directions
so i've really enjoyed that in the past
but i've never had what i would call a
spiritual experience
what's the mystery
of the disappearance of the indus valley
civilization there's no mystery it's
never disappeared
still exists
it's us
why do some scientists and
mathematicians like john nash and
vashisht narayan singh
suffer from schizophrenia well
there are lots of scientists and
mathematicians who don't suffer from
schizophrenia but these are interesting
individuals because they were able to do
good work
excellent work
despite being schizophrenics and that's
why their stories are more famous
so i would say that there is no
correlation between
mental illness
and mathematics
or mental illness and being a genius
being a genius means you have a
different mental makeup for sure
but it doesn't necessarily mean that you
are more predisposed to
having any mental illnesses
so uh i don't personally quite see a
correlation between being a genius
scientist
or being a genius mathematician and
having
schizophrenia or any other mental
illness because i know of many many
such geniuses who were perfectly fine
so the thing about schizophrenia is that
it seems to run in families right
for instance john nash
he had i think two sons
out of which one of his sons was also a
mathematician
and he also had schizophrenia i'm not
sure if he's still alive hopefully he is
but yeah so i think it's a
genetic thing it's a hereditary thing
and
so that's the little i know about
schizophrenia
it's where you have these experiences
right you hear you hear voices and you
imagine
people who don't exist that sort of
thing
all right
really
i didn't know this ukraine officially
asked india to security provider
okay first of all i haven't heard about
this if they have really asked for it we
should immediately say that it is not
our war
what's happening in ukraine is not
india's business
it's not india's responsibility to
provide security to ukraine
i know things are bad but it's it's very
unfortunate and we can
offer us offer them our
sincere
condolences for what's happening but
it's not our war
india will not get involved
in a war that is not something we
started and not something we are
responsible for
so if the ukrainians ask india
to provide security we must say
very sorry
we are sorry for what's happening to you
but we cannot do it
simple
so the target is 150
that's what daily capitals made
so lsg is 71 for no loss in nine hours
uh lucknow supergiants
and kuldeep kuldeep singh the the lefty
leg spinners bowling
and uh quentin is batting well it looks
like
quintin de
akshay says why are north sentinel
people so hostile because there is a
history
the british colonizers
set foot there
and they brutalized those people there
was this british guy whose name i don't
remember anymore because he's an
insignificant guy but what he did is
that he
um
what he did is that he set foot on that
place with his soldiers and all that he
was in charge of the soldiers and he
took many of these people as as
prisoners and did weird things with them
not quite sure what the weirdness was
but there was some weirdness there
so the experience that the people
of this island had
with outsiders was not good
so that will be passed on from
generation to generation that story and
that's why there is this
hostility to outsiders
so from their perspective they have been
stranded on that island
for 40 000 years or so
and for them
whether it is
somebody from britain or somebody from
india
or somebody from sri lanka it's all the
same it's outsiders
and based on the experience they have
with the british outsiders are bad and
that's why they are hostile
that's why they are like
they they believe in self-preservation
outsiders do bad things to us so let's
kill them all
so that's why they shoot arrows at
outsiders
and i'm glad that the indian government
has decided to respect their wishes and
not interfere with them so north central
and ireland is essentially
an autonomous indian protectorate it is
autonomous because it is
self-administered
india does not impose indian law and
indian constitution on on that island
and they are allowed to live their life
as they wish
and they are under our protection which
is a very good thing and no one is
allowed to go there so that there is no
genetic contamination or no transmission
of illnesses that these guys may not be
immune towards
immune to
so that is the situation with this
island
and these people
okay mahakal says can you suggest a book
you want a 19 year old a bijit
or people in the 20s to read i would say
read everything read as much as you can
acquire as much knowledge as you can and
if you don't like reading
watch podcasts or listen to podcasts or
watch documentaries or whatever works
for you
but acquire knowledge
so i don't have any see the thing
i don't have a single book that i can
recommend
what i can recommend is read lots of
books
broaden your horizons
if you read a book
it's very problematic don't ever read a
book
read all books you can
all right
i uh people who read only
one or two books this scare me
all right
gary josh says
your views on near death experience or
out of body experience
it's a fact it happens
it happens to lots of people
so my views are that we don't quite know
what is the cause of these
experiences
uh
people uh who whose heart is taught for
instance and they are revived
they uh speak about these things
and people who are
in a coma so they speak about these
things so these are called near death
experiences and out of body experience
so in some cases they feel like they
they remember being out of the body
no longer being part of the body being
somewhere else maybe on the ceiling or
something and watching themselves being
operated upon whatever so this is a
reasonably common
experience that people have who go
through such uh
circumstances
and while this out of why this
near-death experience of being inside a
tunnel and seeing some entities
that may possibly be exp be explained
by chemical imbalances or whatever in
the brain but how do you explain the out
of body experience in which you are
outside of the body and you see
you remember seeing yourself
be lying on the table or whatever the
doctor's trying to revive you how do you
explain that
so there are certain things that still
cannot be adequately exp explained
by whatever knowledge we have i'm sure
there are explanations but
so
i think
the thing is it's still
to a large extent
a mystery and it's not
properly understood
and thus far
it has not been sufficiently well
explained as to why this happens
so that is my view on this it's a very
interesting topic fascinating topic
that's what i can say about it
okay let's let's go back to cricket oh
one guy is out who is out
so mr rahul is gone
74 for one in 10 hours
they need 150 in 20.
okay i guess
they could they could still achieve it
they are on track
okay
daniel says doctor strange represent
what is that
doctor strange is one of those marvel
superhero people right
a guy dude does this weird thing
and travel through time and all that
okay what else do we have
uh your thoughts on samadhi and maha
samadhi
uh
i don't quite know much about this
samadhi means
what is samadhi it is a very deep state
of meditation right samadhi and
mahasamadhi may be something even deeper
than that
um so
so yeah that's that's
what i know about this it's all about
stages of meditation
to what what level you can meditate
and some people give up their bodies
during samadhi right they just
see yeah so and you find these uh
these samadhi's of various ancient
saints in some places so when
a person goes into samadhi and never
comes back they're buried they're not
they're not cremated right so
so that's the little i know about this
it's an interesting topic again
but that's that's all i could
say about it as of as of today
ashish says the difference between turks
mughals and afghans
turks and mughals are the same thing
that the mughals would talks
they are called mughals for some reason
because maybe they claim to have
mongolian ancestry so that's why they
the term mughal was
was used for them but they were actually
turks
culturally they were tugs they may have
had some partial fragmentary mongol
ancestry to some extent but culturally
religiously
in all that they were turkic
so so the the people we called mughals
were accurate talks
so the turks were these central asian
nomads descendants of the hunnic peoples
they followed various religions at
different points in time their ancestral
culture was what is known as tangerism
which is a polytheistic belief system
uh
then they also
they also followed at different times
hinduism and buddhism
then eventually they all became muslim
so that's what you see among the turks
today
so the mughals
the so-called mughals were actually
turks
the turks of turkey are turks the turks
of central asia are also turks the
afghans are not turks
the afghans
well
today it's complicated
but if you look at the history of
gandhar the indians
so if you look at the population
the the
ethnic
makeup of afghanistan you have a number
of distinct ethnic groups
in afghanistan today
the largest ethnic group is the pashtuns
then you have the uzbeks
you have the turkmen to some extent you
have the hazaras
and you also have the tajiks
so the uzbeks
the the the hazaras the uzbeks are turks
the hazaras are of mongolian origin
the
tajiks
are
indo-iranian and the pashtuns are of
indian origin
you you say this to a pashtun they'll
get angry they said i am we are not
indians we are what
we are either iranians or we are
descendants of jews or something they
will say
but
if you look at the genetics it is clear
that they are indians they are of indian
origin they are an extension of the
overall north indian population
so the true afghans are the pashtuns
and they are the descendants of ancient
indians
okay what else do we have
okay tell us about william the conqueror
he is considered a villain in the uk
because he conquered their country long
ago
was he a brutal mass murderer as they
say he is not considered to be a villain
in the uk from what i know
from what i know
he is the ancestor of the british royal
ruling family royal family
every single
king or queen of england
from the year 1066 onwards
was a direct descendant of william the
conqueror
so he is
the ancestor of all
their kings and queens from the past
1000 years
and so so i from my perspective i don't
see
this sort of attitude towards william
the conqueror
most likely they consider him to be one
of the one of the greatest rulers
so what is the truth about this guy
he was born an illegitimate child
so the story is very interesting uh his
ancestor his great great great
grandfather or whatever
was a viking
named rollo
and he settled down in west northwest in
france what's known as normandy
uh
and he settled down there with
his viking followers
and they adopted french customs
french language they married french
women
and they adopted the french language so
eventually they became french after two
three generations
so this guy so they became so rollo was
the first duke of normandy
and his overlord was the king of france
and he began a line of dukes of normandy
his son was the duke of normandy the
second duke his grandson was the third
duke and so on so
so this guy william
was either his great great brunson or
great great great gunson i don't
remember quite
but he was an illegitimate child that's
why
he was given this disrespectful epithet
of william the bastard
that's what they used to call him
so he had a
reasonably good
reign as the duke of normandy he was a
very vigorous military campaigner
it is possible that he was even more
powerful than the king of france
and then in the year 1066 he invaded
england
and he got lucky
and he was able to
conquer england from that time onwards
nobody called him william the bastard
they called him william the conqueror
so
that's the brief story of this guy
he was brutal whenever he needed to be
his final act as the king was the
destruction of the city of north in
france
he set the city on fire and he killed a
whole bunch of people men women children
so yeah he was brutal
that's how it always was the history of
humanity is a history of
of conflict warfare and brutality so
yeah he was brutal and
he disempowered the saxon
elite of england
and he replaced the saxon nobility with
the norman nobility and eventually it
all merged over time over the centuries
and that's how it happened
so that is in brief about william the
conqueror
excuse me
vijay vaguela says do you watch golf
no i don't
i don't quite understand golf i have a
very very
very rough idea of how the game is
played this the lower your score the
better you've done that sort of thing
so
that's that's
what i know about it i know that they
have had a few good players
tiger woods comes to mind and
greg norman i believe
and so on that's the little i know about
golf i've never really been a golf guy
never watched golf
so
that's where i stand with respect to
golf
okay
okay pages says if you say mongols
respected indian culture why did they
not overthrow iltutmish and free us from
the invaders
because it was not their fight
i can respect ukrainian culture
but it doesn't make make it my
responsibility to go and defeat vladimir
putin and get him out of ukraine it's
not my fight it's not my war
similarly ching is khan was
standing on the western banks of the
indus river
uh 800 years before today
maybe seven nineteen ninety maybe eight
hundred one years before today whatever
it is
but it was not his fight
he had
other problems to deal with
his own national interest
to
safeguard
and there was a big rebellion on going
in china at the time he had conquered
china but because he went all the way
west to
the kingdom the empire of kharasma which
is
like 3 000 kilometers away the chinese
rebelled and they declared independence
so he had to go back and quell that
rebellion
that was the pressing concern for him it
was a matter of life and death for for
his people in the long run
so that's why he had to go and deal with
that and the india's problems were
india's problems you guys deal with it i
respect your culture i will not harm you
but i will not go and waste my time
saving you you that's what you need to
do for yourself
so that's how it is
just because you respect somebody
doesn't mean that that person becomes
your responsibility
all right
why are there graves of ancient indians
if indians practice cremation
maybe we have been practicing cremation
for a few thousand years
maybe before that we practiced burials
there is nothing
in the vedic texts
or in what we call hinduism that says
that you cannot practice burials
right
so india's history as a civilization
is
close to 10 000 years old
we may have and we are a very diverse
people
we are very diverse people we have lots
of local manifestations of the overall
indian culture and civilization
so even today there are certain uh
people in southern india i believe who
who are hindus
who even today practice
burials
so there is nothing in the hindu
so-called religion that says you can't
have burials
it's your choice but
overall as as a people we kept we
practice
cremations
so
our history is very old and a whole lot
of changes have happened
over the millennia
so that's why you will find graves also
in ancient india so there's nothing
that suggests
that this is not part of indian culture
all right where are we now
mayuri says what's your views on this
youtube personality called jordan
peterson
have you been interested in the topics
he has spoken about he's not really a
youtube personality he's a professor
just because he's a youtube channel
doesn't mean
he's a mere youtuber he is a
he is he transcends youtube
and he is quite influential among
certain sections of western society
uh he's more of a traditionalist he's
strongly christian
in his belief system so i have watched a
few of his videos i even have his book
but i haven't quite read it thus far
which book
those 12 habits he speaks about
i have also
read parts of his older book
so what i see about in him is that he is
strongly
christian he believes in western
civilization he believes in the in the
supremacy of western civilization he
believes that it is the superior
civilization all progress that humanity
has achieved is because of
the excellence of western civilization
he believes in christian values in
traditional values
and so on and so forth
so that's what i can say in brief about
jordan peterson
um yeah
so yeah
he's an interesting person
i don't
agree with him on everything or on many
things
all right
[Music]
why is the government of india not
resuming excavations in dwarka
who is stopping them the only thing that
is stopping the indian government is the
indian government i don't know why the
excavation
is not
being carried forward
no idea
it should happen it needs to happen
rishikesh says even if pakistan is
balkanized a nuclear state would remain
how does india deal with that this is
this is a good question
rishikesh
i must applaud you for asking this
excellent question we speak about
balkanizing pakistan
what happens to the nukes
so
let's go back to the early 90s 1990s the
americans
successfully balkanized
the ussr
and yet they were not able to solve the
problem of the nukes
so out of the
out of the fragments and debris
of the ussr
came a successor state
which was russia
at that time they had a puppet called
boris yeltsin in power who essentially
did their job further and destroyed the
russian economy
and yet
after he came vladimir putin
who
over two decades worked towards
rebuilding
uh the russian economy
and
he made russia more powerful again it's
not a superpower anymore but it is still
a major global power
and they have more nukes than the us
so
despite being successful
in balkanizing the ussr
the americans were not able to solve the
question to resolve the question of the
nukes the news are still there
and they now belong to russia
so if pakistan is balkanized
the question is what happens to the
nukes that they have
so
i don't have the answer today
that is something india's leadership
needs to think about
it is a problem that needs to be solved
merely balkanizing pakistan will not be
enough
they will have to find a way of
securing
the nukes
or neutralizing the nukes i would say
securing them would be a better option
so how to engineer that
there are
there are ways of doing that
there are creative ways of doing such
things
you need to cultivate people within the
establishment it can be done of course
it can be done
so that's the problem that
the indian state the indian government
the leadership will have to grapple with
i'm sure there must be multiple plans
and alternatives in place
so yeah the best way to secure nukes in
an enemy state
when you balkanize it is to cultivate
people whom you can trust within
the establishment of that state
which means within the pakistan army
itself or the isi
so that's what would need to be done so
when the breakup happens
those nukes
for a few hours should be safely in the
custody of those people until they can
be
they can be handed over to somebody more
responsible like the indian government
so that's something that would need to
happen
all right
okay what else do we have uh
mac per 20 thank you so much appreciate
it
uh vijandra singh says can you please
tell us about the charan community and
why they are not included in the caste
system we don't have a caste system in
india we have the varnajati system which
is way more complex and complicated and
and intricate then this
ridiculous
forecast system
let me let me tell you something
we all believe in this
we all believe that we have been
practicing this chatur varna system or
something
right and it's mentioned in certain
certain ancient texts like the
manuscript etc but look at
how india used to be
if you see the accounts of the greek
ambassador to india megasthenes
so this guy this greek ambassador was in
the
indian emperor's court in patliputra
during the mauryan era and he wrote a
detailed account of india
he wrote a book or or an account called
indica now the original text is lost but
it is referenced multiple times in other
texts that have survived so we know what
magastanis wrote about india
in the text that is lost so what he said
is that there were seven classes in
india seven
seven
not four seven classes
and he did not call them castes or
whatever there were seven different
categories of occupations
or people in india
and uh
you had all these different
things that they took care of you had
the brahmins who were the people who
took care of the knowledge and imparting
and transmitting knowledge
you had
philosophers
you had laborers you had farmers the
farmers were the most numerous people
and the most prosperous most likely
and then you had the warriors
and
so so you can look it up i don't
remember the exact
uh details of each of these seven
categories but you had seven
distinct classes of people in india
so this chaturvarna system is something
that has
crept into our consciousness at a much
later date
and it is something that is now ossified
and it's become a reality
because in any government form or
certificate you
you essentially need to write down your
caste
whether you are going for admission or
and because of the reservation system
also so the charan community as far as i
know it is uh
they used to be
what did what was their
their their their occupation they were
record keepers they were bards
singers
and to some extent warriors too i
believe if required
so
so that's
that's what i remember about the charon
community vaguely
so they are closely associated with the
with the with the aristocracy of the
of the region of western india
so rajput and charans are closely
associated as far as i recall
so that's what i could offer to you in
brief i am not an expert in the history
of the charan people but
they have had a significant role to play
in the in the
history of india at least the past
thousand
maybe two thousand years
okay paranjal says how do i prepare for
the upsc
as the you is the history books
recommended for upsc are marxist
agenda-driven history
upsc is biased towards the left so how
do i qualify later change within
listen if you want to
qualify for the ups you have to read
those history books
and pass the exams so all you have to do
is tell yourself that this is not the
correct history but since they require
me to answer in a certain way i will
answer in that way that they require
but you don't have to internalize that
right
so it's as simple as that if you want to
make a career for yourself in the upsc
uh then you have to go through this
this process
of
absorbing and then replicating that
false distorted history but don't
internalize it always remind yourself
that this is something
that i am going
to do as a temporary thing
so that's what i could say in brief
all right all right um
okay somebody is disagreeing with me sir
thank you thank you very much
i know that the kayasthas were record
keepers and administrators and
bookkeepers the charans like i said were
bards
they were good in singing and they would
extol the virtues of the rulers
and the ancestors and things like that
and to some extent they also maintained
genealogical records please prove me
wrong
all right
ah there you go
so neil says philosophers cultivators
herdsmen artisans and traders
soldiers overseers and counselors one
two three four five six seven these are
the seven
classes or categories of people that
were there in india
two and a half thousand years ago so
there were not four castes you had these
seven categories or classes of people
and i'm sure there was social mobility
based upon your aptitude and and your
performance and whatever you're good at
so that's what india used to be like
don't believe this nonsense of the four
castes and all that it's never been that
way
what is the purpose of human existence
don't believe in maya
what's the purpose of existence
to do something good to live a good life
that when you are leaving it should not
fill you with regret
we don't know what the what the true
nature of the universe is we know very
little
we don't understand
we have the faintest idea
of
about
four percent of the universe
more than 96 percent of the universe is
dark
so we don't know what's going on there
we don't know if there is something
beyond our universe and we don't know
what consciousness is there is so much
we don't know
so the
so
so what i would say is that
nobody has the real answers
some people claim to have the answers
okay that's good good for them i don't
have the answers
but what i could say is that
the purpose of life is to live the kind
of life that when you leave that life
when it comes to an end you should not
look back upon your life and
be filled with regret do something
constructive
do something creative leave something
behind that will be useful for others
help others
make others happy without making
yourself unhappy in the process
don't let people exploit you but create
something
leave something behind that is useful
for others be a good link in the chain
we are simply links in the chain between
the past and the future so be a good
link don't be a
rotten link
right
so that's what i would say is the
purpose of human existence
i think the most fulfilling thing is to
help is to contribute something good to
society in any way whatsoever in a small
way or a big way it doesn't matter
but don't cause any harm
don't cause
hurt be good
and and if possible create something
good that that in my op in my personal
opinion
is the purpose of human existence
who is king solomon did he have any ties
with india king solomon was one of one
of the oldest
kings of the jews
he is believed to have lived about 3000
years before today
some people consider him to be a
historical king some people
consider him to be a semi-mythical king
i would say most likely he was a
historical king
and he built this great temple in the
city of yerushalayim jerusalem
and that temple was destroyed by the
romans
and one of its walls still stands
they call it the veiling wall it's a
sacred site for the jews for the jewish
people for the yahudhi people so that is
in very brief who king solomon was
and did he have ties with india
there is no evidence that he had any
so from the limited knowledge that i
have i have not seen any evidence of
ties between the indian people indian
civilization and the
jewish people from the time of king
solomon 3000 years before today
okay
what is the current status of active
indian overseas military bases that's a
good question so
we have a number of active military
bases outside of our country on the
territory and soil of other countries
for instance
there is there are two
air force bases
that we may
have
which may be operational in tajikistan
so if you don't know where it is google
it
it is to the north west of afghanistan
it is
a few minutes by air from pakistan
so india has
far core air base and ini air base there
are two air bases in tajikistan
tajikistan is part of india's extended
neighborhood
culturally genetically close to us these
people so that's two air bases that we
have we may or may not have a few
fighter planes there sukhois perhaps and
we may or may not have a few missiles
there possibly perhaps
i i don't have any information okay i'm
just guessing this is called guess work
but
it's reasonably educated guesswork you
could you could call it that so that is
tajikistan
we also have
something in
in oman
a naval base
of some kind
in oman oman is one of our neighboring
nations in case you don't know to the
west of gujarat
if you cross the
sea of savarashtra you will reach oman
so that is oman we have some kind of
naval facility in oman at least one we
may have something in
chabahar
which is in iran
and we certainly have radar stations in
the seychelles
which is in the indian ocean between
between india and
madagascar
and we also have an island
that we have leased from mauritius
on which we may have some kind of naval
and other kinds of
naval facility and maybe something else
so that's what i can think of off the
top of my head
do we have anything else
we have a significant collaboration with
france in the indian ocean region
france in case you don't know is a major
indian ocean naval power
and
so yeah that's what i can say do we have
anything else elsewhere
uh overseas military base that's what i
can think of right now
so yeah that's what i can say in brief
about our
active overseas military
bases
so what is happening in the ipl let me
see
mr quinton is raising his bat he seems
to have done well
so lsg is 106 for two 14.2 overs
and there you go four runs six runs
so looks like lsg is going to win this
match that's what it looks like to me
unless there's a ridiculous collapse of
some kind and given these flat pitches
oh lord shardul is bowling i like the
guy
lord chardul the thing about shardol is
that he is slightly large isn't he
he seems to love
certain kinds of
it's a four it's a four it's not a six
okay
so someone's conversation let me jump
into that which says tanya some kapoor
chopras are aryan
what is
are indo-iranic but not aryan vedic like
iranians and indians
but some kapoors are vedic i'm totally
confused i have lost all track of
history
somebody help
some okay i i don't mean to make fun of
anyone i'm just confused when i see this
some kapoors are pashtun
chopras and tandons are aryans
kapoors are indo-iranic
but not aryan and not vedic like
iranians and indians
but sam kapoor are vedic
that's it i'm done no more history for
me
oh
i have no idea what this means guys
daniel says your thoughts on the our
place social experiment
on reddit
no no thoughts because i haven't heard
of it but what what is it can someone
tell me in the comments
in the chat
what was that
i will certainly look it up
what's your take on global temperatures
rising is it time to globally work on it
together
and give up world politics are we at the
verge of extinction we're not on the
verge of extinction but it's certainly
going to change the world as it is
see
climate change is a thing
there is a human component to it
what what what the
huma what human
what the western nations have done since
the time of the so-called industrial
revolution is to emit incredible amounts
of carbon into the atmosphere
they have been polluting the porsche
atmosphere and
the rivers in the oceans
for
at least two and a half three centuries
more than that most likely
so that has contributed
to climate change and today in the 21st
and 20th 21st century
nations like india and china are trying
to industrialize again
so that's that will have a carbon
footprint you can't blame india for
trying to catch up with what the west
has done and you can't blame china for
that
so that is something that's going to
happen there is a human component to
climate change but even before all of
this there was climate change
we lost the mother of india's
civilization the saraswati river took
climate change
the great river dried out about
three and a half or four thousand years
before today
it was a long slow process that lasted
at least a couple of thousand years
because the indian monsoon started
declining monotonically about six
thousand years before today and that was
the beginning of the decline of the
saraswati
river and that process took at least
2000 years two and a half thousand years
so that is climate change it is a
natural process but it is also being
accelerated
by
human
actions
so it's not going to
render humanity extinct
what could destroy humanity is nuclear
war civil war
what could destroy humanity is
poisoning the oceans
now they're detecting microplastic
particles in human blood
so that could have long term unforced
inconsequences health consequences and
so on
so
i believe
this is my personal opinion
we cannot prevent climate change
it's going to happen it's a natural
process and even the human mediated
factor
on climate to climate change is
something that is irreversible
even if we stop whatever greenhouse
gases are being emitted
and
shift completely to non-two
to renewable energy and all that still
you're gonna have climate change and
what's happened is not going to be
reversed
and it is i believe impossible for
humanity to reach reach a consensus
and for nations to give up their
national interest
so it's going to continue it's going to
keep on happening
so
so yeah that's where we are
globally work together you can globally
work together only if there is a single
world government which would be the most
horrible thing
that can ever happen to humanity
so that is
not going to happen most likely and
hopefully not but
but yeah climate change is gonna gonna
go on
okay
so lsg needs 38 runs from 29 balls
they should win they've lost 22 wickets
okay
aryan says have you heard about the
petroga
petrography of ratanagiri what you mean
is the petroglyphs of ratnagiri which
are these rock carvings yes i've heard
of them very old
they are supposed they are believed to
be more than ten thousand years old in
some cases maybe twelve fifteen thousand
years old so it is evidence of any of an
earlier phase of a more ancient phase of
indian civilization
so yes so
it is something that needs to be
investigated by professional historians
and first of all we need to ensure that
there is proper conservation done of
this
so when something becomes a tourist
attraction people go there and they
damage it
so we need to ensure that these rock
carvings are
preserved properly and safeguarded
and of course we need to find out who
did this what was the cultural
civilizational context is there some
religious significance what was the
significance why did people go to the
trouble of doing all these big rock
carvings
so yeah that's what needs to happen
how to survive a nuclear attack be as
far away from it as possible hopefully
a few hundred kilometers from there then
you will survive it if you are anywhere
within the radius of harm
you're gonna
you're gonna be
affected by it
how to deal with the fragmentation of
social structure and the fading of
culture morals values etc with
materialistic development of a country
the best example is the us and western
countries you know
yeah it's a good question uh it's
something that's happening to india
right now and why is it happening do you
understand
in the past india was the world's
greatest economy the largest economy
so you had incredible material
development
of india
india was a fully urbanized
fully industrialized civilization
four thousand five thousand years before
today we know that
so
there was incredible material
development and yet we had this
incredibly rich culture
and it's able to survive until today now
it is fragmenting so it is not material
development that destroys culture
if you are material is materially
materialistically advanced
but you your government and your
leadership promotes the culture
your culture is going to flower
look at the look at india during the
gupta age
it was it is called the golden age of
india
it was a unified india at the time under
one emperor
material prosperity
and
a brilliant cultural renaissance
so material development doesn't
necessarily mean
crumbling and fading of culture morals
values
so what's really happening
is western interference
in india in india's internal affairs
it is
today indians unfortunately have been
brainwashed into thinking that modernity
is westernization
to be modern
to be advanced to be progress to
progress you have to
discard indian culture indian morals
indian values
and take up western and try to emulate
the west
so that is why india's culture is is
in under threat today and also there are
all these
breaking india forces
various
ngos and religious organizations etc
that are funded by external forces
that are seeking to actively re-engineer
india's demographics
so all that is happening right now so
the simple solution is india needs to
become more powerful india's economy
needs to grow
once you reach a certain stage it will
be very difficult for other countries to
interfere the way they are interfering
interfering right now
so as of today india is not a very
powerful country so that needs to change
then we'll be fine
right
so many questions how many do i pick
alok patel says what will happen to the
tibetan leadership after the 14th dalai
lama
the way things are going
the 14th dalai lama could be the last
or maybe you may have a puppet dalai
lama that the chinese communist party
will install
so for instance
there is this uh
what is that other llama the punch and
llama the the
karma i'm not sure
so that is something that is an
institution
that the chinese have stolen
and they have installed their own
llama
karmapa panchan most likely the punch
and llama
so the tibetans had uh appointed their
own punch and llama
as per their ancient practices and the
chinese abducted that boy and he has
disappeared ever since for the past 20
30 years
maybe 20 plus years
and they have appointed a separate a
different
pancho lama of their own
is it the let me just google it quickly
punch in llama or what is it
what is it punch and llama
yes the 11th punch in llama so that's
what the chinese did they hijacked
that institution
now his holiness the the dalai lama
he is old now
he's he is advanced in his years
so one hopes that he lives to a hundred
or something but that that gives us 20
years so once he passes on
the people of tibet will have to appoint
the next dalai lama so what may happen
then
is that the chinese government will
hijack that process and they will
appoint a ccp dalai lama
a chinese communist party sanctioned
dalai lama which will be a
disaster for tibetan culture
so uh
so yeah that's where we stand the
institution
may end with the current dalai lama or
it may be hijacked by the chinese
government
and yeah so that's that's the
possibility as of today the tibetan
leadership is not even there in tibet
there is a tibetan government in exile
which is which has no real power
so there is a sad situation in tibet
okay akra chan says if china
occupies taiwan
will it be a cause of
the west's hegemonic collapse
can china be balkanized and will we see
an independent xinjiang tibet yunnan
excuse me let me drink some water
so
if the chinese
succeed in conquering taiwan
it will be
a disaster
for the u.s when we say the west we mean
the u.s there is only one power
in the west the u.s
so if the chinese succeed in this it
will be a complete disaster for the us
it will it means that the us will lose
its superpower status
so yes if that happens it will be the
cause
of the collapse
of american hegemony in the world the
americans will lose their superpower
status
it could be the beginning of the rise
of a new superpower china
so the americans will try their best not
to
allow this to happen
uh so the other question is can china be
balkanized and so on yeah china can be
balkanized if the right conditions and
are in place
so what are the right conditions well
look at history look at how other other
powers have been balkanized look at how
empires collapse it can happen
so
as of today it is difficult because the
chinese communist party is in complete
control of china there is almost no
resistance to the chinese communist
party they have like 100
hegemony in china
so when you have that level of control
it is difficult to envisage
a collapse of the regime
the one way
in which the ccp could collapse
is if they engage in some kind of
military misadventure
and get beaten
badly
and very publicly
that would
totally destroy their legitimacy their
claim to legitimacy as the only ruler of
china
so i don't see the chinese communist
party doing that because they are very
risk hours they have built a lot
in the past few decades and they don't
want to lose that
so that's why they are very risk covers
aditya says i have three careers in life
entrepreneur
open world biggest company be the first
indian company to do so
politician
and ias
where can i contribute the most to our
great nation to make it greater
i can't give you the answer because i
don't know
you personally i don't know what your
strengths are i don't know what your
weaknesses are everybody has strengths
and everybody has a corresponding set of
weaknesses
so i don't know what your strengths and
aptitudes are some people
will make good entrepreneurs
some people may not do
be that
and some people may be good at politics
some people may be good at bureaucracy
so it is for you to to discover that but
what is the best path for yourself and
to discover that you have to first
understand yourself
so invest the time and the effort in
understanding yourself
and then you will know to answer i
cannot give you the answer
nobody can give you the answers except
yourself
all right um
kieran says putin is claiming that
americans have an intention
of the dissolution of the russian
federation
i saw this in the russia in a russian
government-funded channel of course the
americans intend to do that
they like i said in the beginning of
this uh live stream the americans seek a
bipolar world they seek a g2 kind of
situation
which means
two major powers the us and obviously
china
the americans do not want a multi-polar
world
so as long as nations like russia
and india exist
bipolarity is a pipe dream
and multi-polarity will continue
so the americans need to find a way to
deal with russia and also with india
either by making india a puppet
or a colony of the us
or by
engineering the fragmentation of india
so the americans
have two options with india either make
india puppet or to
engineer the fragmentation of india when
it comes to russia they only have one
option they only have one intention to
balkanize
russia and cause its dissolution
so if putin has said that obviously he
knows what the what the truth is
right so
to understand the american perspective
why would they not want this they don't
want any challenges they don't want
multiple challenges if there is only two
big polls
then they can focus on the one major
challenge which is china but if there
are multiple poles multiple powerful
nations then they have to deal with a
multitude of potential threats and
competitors
so to make things simple they would
prefer to have just
a bipolar world
so one way of doing it is to first deal
with russia and then deal with india
so that is the logic which makes sense
from their perspective
why does china want taiwan
well the chinese want taiwan for
multiple reasons
firstly taiwan they consider taiwan to
be a breakaway province
the people of taiwan
the the
the majority of the population of taiwan
is chinese speaking of chinese origin
so that is one reason secondly the
taiwanese
they have this strong relationship with
the americans and to capture taiwan
means that they would
they would break the american hegemony
in that region and globally so the
chinese
have this aspiration
to replace the us as the global
superpower
so one way of doing it one of the steps
towards the process is to reacquire
taiwan so there are multiple reasons and
they all make sense
if you put yourself in the shoes of the
chinese
from their perspective
of their national interest it makes
sense to
reacquire taiwan
uh pratham says is ramadan khadirov the
successor of putin
we don't know who is the successor of
putin first of all his name is ramzan
kadyrov not ramadan
is the
is the de facto king of chechnya
and
this is the this is the
arrangement that he has with vladimir
putin that he will have reasonably
autonomous
rule in chechnya but he will
recognize putin as the overall emperor
that sort of thing
like you had with the king of france and
the duke of normandy so the duke of
normandy was more or less autonomous in
normandy but he officially recognized
the king of france as his overlord
so that's the kind of situation they
have
and uh
so i don't see ramzan khadirov as the
successor of putin
i don't see that happening that would be
a change of
monumental proportions
and there is no reason for putin to
to
allow somebody like khadirov to become
the ruler of russia he would not allow
that
so uh we don't quite know what
succession plans vladimir putin has
the key to the longevity of a culture of
a civilization of an empire is good
succession
so in the case of the chinese communist
party they have a very clear
mechanism
of succession
the successor to the chinese emperor or
the president whatever you call it comes
from the inner courtery of the chinese
communist party from the inner circle
from the from the elite
so this before uh
before xi jinping your head who was it
was in tao
i think it was
before hoojin tower you had
who was it
lee peng shang jamin before them you had
then shopping okay i get the chronology
mixed up sometimes but
so they have a clear mechanism of how
the succession will happen in the case
of russia we don't quite know what the
mechanism is
but i am sure vladimir putin must have
thought about this
and he must have
two or three potential successors
lined up in his head and
and i suppose that's how it will how it
will happen but i don't see ramzan
kadhirov as being the successor of putin
ethnically he is more of an indo-iranian
person then russian
so yeah that's how i see it
vijay raghavan says please tell us about
russia's
911 which is the best land hostage
crisis
in the chechen
wars the first war the second war
how is chechnya's warlord today a
russian
excuse puppet
so the baseline hostage crisis happened
about
roughly a couple of decades ago
in which you had this chechen rebels
who
took all these hostages
uh was it a theater was it a school
um it was a school they took all these
little kids hostage and many of these
kids died that sort of thing
so it was not a very
good thing to do but well that's how it
goes
so uh what happened is that
after the breakup of the ussr
many of these republics
the soviet socialist republics they
declared independence ukraine became
independent tajikistan became
independent
armenia azerbaijan
kazakhstan
uzbekistan and so on so forth
estonia
they all broke away
from the ussr
now the chechens
who are in the
caucasus region southern russia
they also wanted to break away
and ethnically i mean culturally
religiously they are
they have historically been muslims
so they started this
what you could
consider to be an islamic
insurgency
and they tried to break away
so the russians fought back
during
yeltsin's time there was the first war
with chechnya
which the russians more or less lost
then when vladimir putin came to power
he started the second war
and
this time around the russians won
they reacquired control
over chechnya the city of grozny was
flattened more or less
yeah
that's what happened
and then what what vladimir putin did is
that
he uh
he reached this kind of agreement with
ramzan kadhira
ramzan ramzan kadyrov's father was this
was a very prominent chechen leader he
first fought against russia
then he switched sides and eventually he
was assassinated in uh
in a bombing
so his son is ramzan kadhirov and putin
appointed ramzan kadhirov as the
governor or de facto king of chechnya
and the arrangement is that the this guy
kadhirov has more or less complete
control over chechnya he is like a king
the russians will not interfere with the
internal affairs in chechnya they will
allow them these guys to practice islam
in their own way whichever way they want
the only thing is that they have to
recognize
the supremacy of russia as the
so chechnya has to remain a part of
russia
remain a part of russia
and they must contribute soldiers and
all that
to the russian
military cause whenever required
so ramzan khadirov essentially has his
own private army a chechen army
and it is right now in action in ukraine
so what i just said you are seeing it in
action right now
so that's how it happened the russians
were just too powerful that's why the
chechens reached this compromise
that we will
acquire
local regional autonomy while remaining
subsidiary or subordinate to russia
so that's what happened in very brief
okay what's happening in cricket
super giants need 19 runs in 12 balls
should not be very hard
they've lost three wickets who's batting
deepak huda and krill pandya
yeah should be okay they should be able
to do it
what do you guys think who's winning
yeah so that's where we are
sachit says my question is why are there
so many countries defence ministers
visiting india
recently
is it to change india's position
position with regards to ukraine russia
issue many of them are doing it to
pressurize india some of them are doing
it
to
have a better relationship with india
so when
a u.s ally comes to india
and they want to
whatever is happening it may be on
behalf of the us
to put forth the u.s perspective and to
try and cajole or coerce india into
towing the line
that the u.s wants us to to
so so from that perspective that's
what's happening but there are certain
other people i'm sure i'm not sure if
the french
minister came to india most likely they
did come
so in that case it would be a bilateral
thing and even the russian foreign
minister
came to india last week i believe about
a week or so ago
so everybody has different objectives
and some of them want us to go into the
u.s camp some of them want us to remain
autonomous some of them want
partnerships with india mutually
beneficial partnerships but it's some
one thing is becoming very clear india
has become the focus of a lot of
diplomatic activity in the last month or
so and it's continuing it's it's
happening on a continuing basis
there is this neighborhood first
diplomacy the sri lankan ministers came
to india the nepalese prime minister
came to india
lavrov came to india so so much is
happening
so it looks like india is currently
playing a significant role of some kind
even as a mediator in the ukraine
situation
so um yeah that's where we are today
and what we are witnessing is that india
is standing firm
india is not bowing down to foreign
pressure
to do what is not
to do what's not in india's best
interests
our place is the best i'll have to look
at this what is this our place thing
okay where are we what else is there
this is a very long live stream isn't it
let's let's
continue until the end of the match what
happened here
somebody bowled the ball and was hit for
a sec
is india ready for a war with china
i think india is reasonably ready india
has prepared for various eventualities
we have certain advantages when it comes
to the terrain from the geography
and i don't think the chinese
i don't think it would be very advisable
for the chinese to
engage in a misadventure with india
because we have several
levels
of response ready for the chinese
and i'm not sure the chinese would do
very well
so i think india is reasonably ready
for a potential war with china
but of course we should never be
complacent we should never take anybody
for granted
china is a bigger economy much bigger
economy much powerful much more powerful
military than india
so yes we need to take those things into
account
and
never take
any enemy for granted
all right
it's a funny question somewhere
can bangladesh acquire nukes
i suppose they can
i mean
building
nuclear weapons
isn't that difficult
what you need is reasonably sufficient
quantities of the
highly enriched uranium 235 or plutonium
if you have the right amount of that you
can build nuclear weapon it's not very
difficult
the engineering part is about
miniaturizing your
warhead
so
it should not be very hard for any
nation with nuclear capabilities or
nuclear reactors to
to be able to do this given enough time
and if they're allowed to do that
so
yeah they could acquire nukes it's not
very difficult
i mean i have a video on this channel
about how you can essentially build a
nuclear weapon in your backyard if you
have the
right ingredients
is time and illusion
maybe we don't know what time is
time is one of the great mysteries in
science and in physics
so is time and illusion it's it's been
four hours 12 minutes since this live
stream started is that an illusion no
it's quite real
but what exactly is time
we don't have a clear definition of what
time is in physics we use time
in our differential equations and in our
considerations in our calculations but
we don't know what it is where does time
come from
is time something that emerges out of
some somewhere
is time and emergent property of the
universe
is time quantum in nature are there
atoms and molecules and quanta of time
we don't know we don't have any of these
answers
but it is something that does exist it
is something that's real
so to some extent it's not an illusion
but at a deeper level it may actually be
maybe there is no past present future
maybe it's all at the same
same time
maybe past present future actually exist
at the same
actually co-exist perhaps
so yeah that that's what i could say
where is it
okay subha
the reason for quantum fluctuations in
the early universe
well quantum fluctuations arise out of
the heisenberg uncertainty principle
uh
there is
so according to the heisenberg
uncertainty principle
you cannot measure 2.2 correlated
variables with the greatest with
precision ever
so um position and momentum
for instance if you know exactly where a
particle is
if you know exactly where the position
is you
have a great uncertainty in the momentum
if you know the momentum with a great
amount of certainty there's a great
amount of uncertainty
in the position
and similarly energy and time
so because of this
fundamental quantum property of of
reality
these quantum fluctuations happen
which means that in empty space in
vacuum
you have virtual particle anti-particle
pairs
popping into existence and before the
time window of the heisenberg incentive
as an uncertainty principle closes these
two
particle anti-particle pairs these two
particles they collapse back into
nothingness
so you are borrowing energy from
space-time
and within the time limit you are giving
it back to space-time and this is
something that is experimentally
observed
so essentially this the heisenberg
uncentral uncertainty principle is the
reason
for quantum fluctuations but why is it
so that's a deeper reality that we still
don't know quite
very well about
so quantum mechanics quantum physics is
still very mysterious
but that's what i could say in in brief
the reason for quantum fluctuations
right where is the match going
they need five runs to win from five
balls
hoga yoga
will it happen
bangladesh
is a military coup possible in india
no
not possible
a military coup is not possible in india
now
why am i saying it's not possible that
will take me some time to explain
but if you want to know
read the book by dr edward luthwaak
the name of the book is kudita
so in that book if you read that book
you will understand exactly why a coup
d'etat is not possible
in a country like india whereas it is
possible in countries like pakistan sri
lanka and china
but it's not possible in india
okay
see this this is called wisdom
this is called the real gyan nepal is
the strongest power
nepal lipa nepal is the center of the
universe
how did ancient indians collect
astronomical data
through observations
naked eye observations
as far as we know
telescopes had not been invented in
ancient india as far as we know
so
thousands and thousands of hours
of naked eye observations and recording
of the data
that's how
we collected astronomical data and
that's what the europeans were able to
acquire from us
so if you look at the
uh what is it called
kepler's laws there are three kepler's
laws right
this guy kepler johannes kepler was able
to come up with these three laws
based on data that was acquired from
india
astronomical data
and that's something that they will not
talk about
four runs
done is it
so they need one run from three balls
it's almost done
is it true that india was offered a
permanent seat in the u.n security
council yes it is true
and if you go on onto my twitter account
twitter profile you will find
links to the evidence
multiple links
from multiple sources that all
demonstrate
that india was offered a permanent seat
in the un security council multiple
times in the 1950s
uh
every country shows their history as per
their national interest so how do you
know the true history you can never
really know the true history there's
always some amount of propaganda some
amount of
narrative building narrative
construction and so on
so the best way to know the true history
is to look at hard
evidence like
archaeological evidence
and to look at genetic evidence and to
look at any matter from multiple angles
from multiple perspectives and
and to
read as much
about it as possible from all from all
perspectives
then you will know what the true history
is and there's the six and the match is
over
so lsg have won the match
and mr badoni hit a six
yay
good job
all right so let me take one final
question will india get a permanent seat
in the u.n security council in the next
10 years
the answer is no
and that's not necessarily a bad thing
all right ladies gentlemen friends
indians
non-indians countrymen country women etc
thank you for being here
on this live stream all these all these
four hours
was a great experience so let's do this
again sometime
and i will see you soon
so that brings me to the end of today's
session thank you very much it was great
fun
and we'll do this again
take care
bye